主演：史宾塞·屈塞
伯特·兰开斯特
理查德·威德马克
玛琳·戴德丽
马克西米利安·谢尔
茱迪·嘉兰
片名：纽伦堡大审
纽伦堡，德国 1948年
我不知道会有这么糟.
I didn't know it was so bad.
一系列纵火案， 造就了这大堆的建筑物
A couple of incendiaries, these old buildings go up Iike Cellophane.
在纽伦堡， 新城区和旧城区是分离的.
A wall separates the old section of Nuremberg from the new.
大概有... 大概相隔有多远, 歇米特?
It goes back to... How far does it go back, Schmidt?
1219, 先生  1219.
1 21 9, sir.  1 21 9.
这是纳粹重整旗鼓的地方，不是吗?
This is where the Nazi party held their rallies, isn't it?
西特勒还有其他团体都到这来.
They all came here. Hitler, Goebbels, the whole crew.
德国的千万人民都到此.
Thousands of them, from all over Germany.
(horn)
他一定要把喇叭弄的那么响吗?
Does he have to blow that damn horn so much?
没必要把喇叭弄这么响, 歇米特.
It's not necessary to blow the horn so much, Schmidt.
你们都知道你们的职责吗?  是.
You both know your duties?  Ja.
好，我们到了 有点沧桑的德国.
Well, here we are. A Iittle bit of old Germany.
柏凯特参议员.  柏尔斯上尉, 这是海伍德法官.
Senator Burkette.  Captain Byers, this is Judge Haywood.
柏尔斯将会是你在这的助手.  我的什么?
Byers here will be your aide.  My what?
办事员、导游. 任何你希望我来做的工作.
CIerk, general guide, Iiaison. Any capacity you wish to use me.
他们将是你的后勤补给, 海尔柏斯德夫妇.
This will be your staff, Mr and Mrs Halbestadt.
你好.  下午好.
Hello.  Good afternoon.
下午好，法官大人.
Good afternoon, Your Honour.
欢迎.  你已经见过你的司机了, 歇米特.
Welcome.  You've met your driver, Schmidt.
我24小时随时准备为你服务.
I'm at your service any time you need me. Day or night.
谢谢.
Thanks.
让我们带他继续参观一下其他地方. 丹.
Let's show him around the rest of the place. Dan.
我们现在会客室.
We're in the reception room.
客厅. 书房在那.
Living room. The study is in there.
这层有两个卧房, 楼上有三个.
There are two bedrooms on this floor, three upstairs.
这些家具部分是原有的， 部分是美国军队提供.
The furniture is part antique, part US army.
钢琴有些旧， 不过也是名牌古董.
The piano is showing signs of wear and tear, but it's a genuine Bechstein.
景色不错吧?  是.
Quite a view, isn't it, sir?  Yes.
Uh...
参议员， 我不需要这样的环境
Senator, I really, really don't need all this.
美国政府办事的话总没有错的.
When the US government does something, it does it right.
过去谁住在这里?  一位重要纳粹高官同他太太
Who used to Iive here?  An important Nazi general and his wife.
还有什么应该让海伍德法官知道的呢?
Is there anything else Judge Haywood ought to know?
先生，有什么问题吗?  是
Sir, any questions?  Yes, yes.
你是西点军校出来的，是吧?  是
You're West Point, aren't you?  Yes.
你的第一名字是?  哈里斯. 哈里.
What's your first name?  Harrison. Harry.
好的，哈里 我不是西点军校的.
Well, Harry, Iook. I'm not West Point, and all this formality kind of gets me down.
你这样的规矩让我拘束
It puts me ill at ease. You think it would be too much of an infraction of the rules
你可以直接称呼我法官或者丹好了?
if you were to call me Judge or Dan or something?
好的，法官 我们的日常供给都在军需处办理.
OK, Judge. We do all our shopping at the army commissary.
当地食物不足， 司机知道路的.
There isn't enough food at the Iocal markets. The driver knows where it is.
这是案件的控告资料.
Here's a copy of the indictment of the case.
谢谢.  希望你在此愉快，先生.
Thanks.  I hope you'II be comfortable here, sir.
上尉，我想这里会很舒适的.
Captain, I think the whole state of Maine would be comfortable here.
我的办公室就在隔壁， 可以随时找我.
My office is next to yours, if you need anything.
谢谢  参议员.
Thank you.  Senator.
你觉得我需要三个仆人吗？ 我这样感觉自己像傻瓜.
Do you think I need the three servants? It kind of makes me feel Iike a damn fool.
你看，这也是帮助了他们啊 解决了他们的吃住.
Well, it helps them out as well as you. You see, here they eat.
好，我需要三名仆人
Oh.
Well, I need three servants.
在这你还是需要匹配的助手的，丹.
It's good to have a man of your stature here, Dan.
当然了， 我是美国唯一胜任此项工作的人.
Sure. Sure. I was the only man in America qualified for this job.
你知道我不是首选， 也不是末选.
You know I wasn't the first choice, nor even the tenth.
你知道，我知道  什么意思?
You know it, I know it.  What do you mean?
让我们来面对现实吧， 西特勒这些纳粹高官都自杀了.
Let's face it. Hitler is gone, Goebbels is gone, Goring is gone  committed suicide.
接下来我们来审判医生、商人、法官.
Now we're down to judging the doctors, businessmen and judges.
还有一些觉得他们不应该受审.  那么?
Some think they shouldn't be judged.  So?
这对我是个挑战
It makes for a Iack of candidates for the job.
你必须全力面对
You had to beat the backwoods of Maine to come up with a hick Iike me.
我希望你没有后悔过来  不
I hope you're not sorry you came.  No, I'm not sorry I came.
我只是想让你知道， 我那些尸体埋在哪里.
I just wanted you to know I know where the body is buried.
不，我想审判还是要继续
No, I think the trials should go on.
特别是对德国法官的审判， 更是要继续，希望我能胜任
Especially the trials of the German judges. I hope I'm up to it.
你胜任的
You're up to it.
好了， 放松享受吧
Well, relax. Enjoy this place while you can.
你接下来要忙一阵了  谢谢，参议员
You're gonna be a pretty busy fellow.  Thanks, Senator.
明天见，法官
See you tomorrow, Judge.
我们要把行李提上去吗?
Shall we, uh, take these upstairs?
哦，好的， 谢谢
Oh, yes, thank you.
那个我可以提.  不，请让我来吧
Here, I can take that one.  No, Iet me take it. PIease.
(man) Here they come.
现在开庭.
The tribunal is now in session.
上帝保佑美国及其高贵的法官席.
God bless the United States and this honourable tribunal.
法庭现在传讯被告.
The tribunal will now arraign the defendants.
为被告爱米尔·哈恩准备了扩音器.
A microphone will be placed in front of the defendant Emil Hahn.
爱米尔·哈恩, 你对法官席的审判有无异议?
Emil Hahn, are you represented by counsel before this tribunal?
(translates into German)
无罪.
(speaks German)
Not guilty.
现在问题是你是否对控诉有辩解?
The question was are you represented by counsel?
(translates into German)
我有异议
(speaks German)
你对控诉所列的内容,
I am represented.
How do you plead to the charges and specifications in the indictment,
承认有罪还是无罪?
guilty or not guilty?
(speaks German)
所有事项均不认罪
Not guilty on all counts.
弗里德·霍夫斯特.
Friedrich Hofstetter.
对控诉你是否需要辩解?
Are you represented by counsel before this tribunal?
(speaks German)
我要辩解  对控诉内容，承认有罪无罪?
I am represented.  How do you plead, guilty or not guilty?
无罪
Nicht schuldig.
你可以坐下了
(Haywood) You may be seated.
沃纳·兰谱.
Werner Lampe.
对控诉你是否需要辩解?
Are you represented by counsel before this tribunal?
控诉?
Counsel?
(speaks German)
当然，当然要辩解
Yes, yes, of course, I am represented.
对检查官的控诉是否认罪?
How do you plead to the charges, guilty or not guilty?
无罪
Nicht schuldig.
你可以坐下了
You may be seated.
欧内斯特·姜宁.
Ernst Janning.
欧内斯特·姜宁, 对控诉你是否需要辩解?
Ernst Janning, are you represented by counsel before this tribunal?
(lawyer speaks German)
法官大人， 我为被告辩护.
I represent the defendant, Your Honour.
对检查官的控诉是否认罪?
How do you plead to the charges and specifications
set forth in the indictment against you, guilty or not guilty?
(speaks German)
法官大人， 我可以庭上发言吗?
Your Honour, may I address the court?
(speaks German)
原告对法庭的审判权力表示怀疑
The defendant does not recognise the authority of this tribunal
为此提出异议
and wishes to Iodge a formal protest.
不认罪的请求将被记录
A plea of not guilty will be entered.
检查官可以进行开幕词了.
The prosecution will begin its opening address.
放松点.
SIow and easy, Junior.
这件案子很特别
The case is unusual, in that the defendants are charged with crimes
是涉及到是否对法律忠诚的案子
committed in the name of the Iaw.
这些在席的被告， 同死去的他们的同僚,
These men, together with their deceased or fugitive colleagues,
都是所谓第三帝国（西特勒统治的德国） 正义的化身.
are the embodiment of what passed for justice during the Third Reich.
在第三帝国时期， 被告们担任法官.
The defendants served as judges during the period of the Third Reich.
如同法官大人你们一样,
Therefore you, Your Honours, as judges on the bench,
坐在法官席上.
will be sitting in judgment of judges in the dock.
这本该如此.
And this is as it should be.
因为只有法官更明白法庭的意义 不只在于它是法庭.
For only a judge knows how much more a court is than a courtroom.
它是一种程序和精神
It is a process and a spirit.
是法律的殿堂
It is the house of Iaw.
被告们也都熟悉法律.
The defendants knew this too. They knew courtrooms well.
他们穿着法官袍 却扭曲了法律,
They sat in their black robes and they distorted, they perverted,
毁坏了德国法律的正义.
they destroyed justice and Iaw in Germany.
公诉人请留意灯.
The prosecution will please watch the Iight.
翻译跟不上你的速度.  对不起，法官大人
The interpreter cannot follow you.  I'm sorry, Your Honour.
他们扭曲法律
They distorted, they perverted,
曲解正义.
they destroyed justice and Iaw in Germany.
这无疑是重大的犯罪
This in itself is undoubtedly a great crime.
但是检查团不是要控诉被告
But the prosecution is not calling the defendants to account
藐视法律
for violating constitutional guaranties or withholding due process of Iaw.
检查团控诉被告谋杀,
The prosecution is calling them to account for murder,
暴行,
brutalities,
拷打等残酷行为,
torture, atrocities!
他们同第三帝国的领导者是同谋,
They share, with all the Ieaders of the Third Reich,
应该为所有的恶行负责,
responsibility for the most malignant, the most calculated,
对全人类负责.
the most devastating crimes in the history of all mankind.
他们的罪孽比其他人可能还要重,
They are perhaps more guilty than some of the others,
因为在西特勒上台以前他们就在这样操作.
for they had attained maturity Iong before Hitler's rise to power.
他们的思想在纳粹催化前就成熟了.
Their minds weren't warped at an early age by Nazi teachings.
本该是重视正义的时候,
They embraced the ideologies of the Third Reich as educated adults,
他们却如此教育德国.
when they, most of all, should have valued justice.
这里他们将要接受他们拒绝的正义.
Here they'II receive the justice they denied others.
他们将当庭根据所有证据被判决.
They'II be judged according to the evidence presented in this courtroom.
公诉人发言完毕.
The prosecution asks nothing more.
罗尔福致开幕词
Herr Rolfe will make the opening statement for the defence.
(speaks German)
尊敬的法官席.
(interpreter) May it please the tribunal.
(speaks German)
这是荣誉...
(interpreter) It is not only a great honour...
也是挑战...
but also a great challenge...
像舆论倡导的一样...
for an advocate...to aid this tribunal in its task.
整个世界都在关注这次的审判
The entire civilised world will follow closely what we do here.
因为这不是普通的审判,
For this is not an ordinary trial,
无论如何这不是一般意义的审判.
by any means of the accepted parochial sense.
审判的目的
The avowed purpose of this tribunal
远非只是审理这么几个人
(in English) is broader than the visiting of retribution on a few men.
这是献身于正义的殿堂.
It is dedicated to the reconsecration of the temple of justice.
这是为了寻找全世界应该负责的正义.
It is dedicated to finding a code of justice the whole world will be responsible to.
这样的原则如何确立?
How will this code be established?
这就要客观的评价
It will be established
真实准确的衡量检查官
in a clear, honest evaluation of the responsibility for the crimes
所指控的犯罪
in the indictment stated by the prosecution.
引用美国法理学家 奥立弗·温德尔·福尔摩斯的话说,
In the words of the great American jurist OIiver Wendell Holmes,
"这种责任不仅要在表面文档查找
"This responsibility will not be found only in documents that no one contests or denies."
"而是要从社会的本质中探询."
"It will be found in considerations of a political or social nature."
"最重要的还是要探索人性."
"It will be found, most of all, in the character of men."
欧内斯特·姜宁的人性如何?
What is the character of Ernst Janning?
让我们简略回顾他的人生吧.
Let us examine his Iife for a moment.
他出生于1885年
He was born in 1 885.
在1907年获得法学博士学位.
Received the degree of Doctor of Law in 1 907.
在1914年成为东普鲁士的一名法官.
Became a judge in East Prussia in 1 91 4.
在“一战”期间
Following World War I, he became one of the Weimar Republic Ieaders
他是魏玛宪法的倡导和立法者之一.
and one of the framers of its democratic constitution.
接下来的数年
In subsequent years, he achieved international fame
他不仅以法理学家出名， 他的著作也享誉全球
not only for his work as a great jurist, but also as the author of Iegal textbooks
现今他的著作还在被引用.
which are still used in universities all over the world.
他在1935年担任德国司法部长.
He became Minister of Justice in Germany in 1 935.
如果欧内斯特·姜宁被判有罪,
If Ernst Janning is to be found guilty,
就会发生一系列牵连.
certain implications must arise.
法官不是立法者.
A judge does not make the Iaws.
他是为国家执行法律
He carries out the Iaws of his country.
如同这样陈述 "我的国家，没有对与错"
The statement "My country, right or wrong"
这是美国爱国诗人的语句
was expressed by a great American patriot.
对于德国的爱国者也一样适用.
It is no Iess true for a German patriot.
难道欧内斯特·姜宁不应该执行法律?
Should Ernst Janning have carried out the Iaws of his country?
难道他应该做一个拒绝执法的叛国者?
Or should he have refused to carry them out and become a traitor?
这是这次审判的焦点.
This is the crux of the issue at the bottom of this trial.
在控诉中
The defence is as dedicated to finding responsibility
被告被控诉需要负责
as is the prosecution.
这已经不是审理欧内斯特·姜宁的问题了.
For it is not only Ernst Janning who is on trial here.
而是对全德国人民的审判
It is the German people.
现在休庭.
The tribunal will recess until further notification.
Yeah.
如果没有问题， 柏尔斯待会就会整理好文档了.
If it's all right with you, Byers can file these briefs Iater.
劳森上校的演说很糟糕不是吗?
It was quite a damning speech by Colonel Lawson, wasn't it?
我真怀疑他的控诉
I wonder if those men in the dock can really be responsible
能否成立
for the things he Iisted in the indictment.
我到这已经有两年多了
I've been here two years, and after that Iong
你会发现责任不是事先就准备好了的.
you find that responsibility is not a cut-and-dried thing.
周末你有什么安排?
What are you fellows up to this weekend?
我和太太要去里奇
My wife and I are going to Liege.
那里什么都没有啊， 我去过.
There's nothing in Liege. I've been there.
我儿子的第101天忌日.
My son was in the 1 01 st.
他葬在那里的美国公墓.
He's buried in the American cemetery outside Liege.
对不起.  没关系.
I'm sorry.  That's all right.
星期一见，丹.  恩.
See you Monday, Dan.  Mm.
一起走吗?  不，还要等会
Coming my way?  No, I'm staying here for a moment.
我在等柏尔斯的记录
I'm waiting for some records from Byers.
好
Right.
这里是你要的报告，先生.  谢谢
Here are the reports you asked for, sir.  Thank you.
上尉， 你可以帮我找欧内斯特·姜宁写的书吗?
Captain, do you think you could get me a copy of the books Ernst Janning wrote?
只怕很少  我想都要
There are quite a few of them.  I'd Iike all of them.
还有可以帮我找一份魏玛宪法的复印本吗?
And also a copy of the Weimar constitution. Can you get that for me?
当然 -谢谢.
Yes, of course.  Thank you.
你到这有多久了，上尉?  两年
How Iong have you been here, Captain?  Two years.
两年，那算很久了  是
Two years, that's a Iong time.  Yes, sir.
有朋友吗?  当然
Any friends?  Sure.
德国朋友?  是
German friends?  Yes.
女孩?  是
A girl?  Yes.
她的父母是纳粹， 但她当时只有9岁
Her parents were Nazis, but she was eight when they came in.
我没有问你这个  或许你在这么想
I didn't ask you that.  Maybe you were thinking it.
很自然会想到的
It's natural to think about it.
我想如果有人要介绍她， 最好还是我
I thought if anybody was going to indoctrinate her, it might as well be me.
还有事吗?  不，我想在镇上走走.
Will there be anything else?  No. I think I'II take a walk around town.
可以到老区喝一杯的.
Try the old section for a beer and a sausage.
谢谢
Thank you.
Nicht mehr! Nicht mehr!
Auf Wiedersehen, Opa.
你懂英语吗?  会一点
Do you understand English?  Yes, a Iittle.
她说什么?  她说 "再见，爷爷."
What did she say?  She said "Goodbye, Grandpa."
(# "Wenn wir marschieren")
(Hitler) Vor uns liegt Deutschland,
in uns marschiert Deutschland,
und hinter uns kommt Deutschland.
(cheering)
(# marching band)
他们对你还好吧?  是的，他们没有亏待我.
Are they treating you all right?  Yes. They are treating me all right.
我们在美国权威机构还是有朋友的.
We still have some friends who have contact with the American authorities.
如果他们没有你可以告诉我.  他们没有虐待我
I can tell them if they are not.  They're treating me all right.
姜宁博士...
Doctor Janning...
我们都处于非常尴尬的境地
we are both in an embarrassing position.
我知道你不希望我来做你的律师
I know you didn't want me as your counsel.
我知道你什么都不需要
I know you didn't want anyone.
但我想告诉你一些事情， 你要听吗?
But I must tell you something. Will you Iisten to me?
是
Yes.
我要对你的案子提出异议
I intend to represent your case with complete dignity.
没有什么感情因素,
There will be no appeal to sentiment,
在法庭上没有同情.
there will be no falling at the mercy of the court.
它有自己的游戏规则.
The game will be played according to their own rules.
我们到要看看他们是否有胆量审判你这样的人.
We'II see whether they have the courage to sit in judgment on a man Iike you.
在我看来
The way I see it,
案子的关键是里萨法案
the most important elements in the case are the sterilisation decrees
还有费尔德斯坦·霍夫曼的案子
and the Feldenstein-Hoffman affair.
姜宁博士
Doctor Janning,
我必须告诉你一些事情
I must tell you something.
当我在大学时我就仰慕你
I admired you since I was a boy in the university.
那是因为我想
It was because I thought I might be able to achieve
我也可以追求你所获得的成就
some of the things you have done
即使在战争时期也是如此
that saw me through the war.
你是我们的偶像
You have been somebody to Iook up to for all of us.
说完了吗, 罗夫曼?
Is that all, Herr Rolfe?
是  谢谢
Yes.  Thank you.
威克博士， 你认识被告欧内斯特·姜宁吗?
Dr Wieck, do you know the defendant Ernst Janning?
是，我认识
Yes, I know him.
可以告诉我们如何认识的吗?
Will you tell us in what capacity?
在1929到1935我们一起在司法部工作.
We served in the Ministry of Justice together from 1 929 till 1 935.
在这之前你们认识吗?  是，他是我的学生.
Did you know him before that?  Yes. He was a Iaw student of mine.
你了解他吗？  是
Did you know him well?  Yes.
他是受你教导吗?  是.
Was he a protege of yours?  Yes.
为什么?
Why?
因为他是个很聪明的人.
He was always a man of great intelligence.
他天生有法律的头脑.
He was a man born with the qualities of a great Iegal mind.
威克博士...
Dr Wieck, would you, uh...
你能否从你的角度告诉我们,
would you tell us, from your own experience,
德国司法部是否受阿道夫·西特勒控制?
the position of the judge in Germany prior to the advent of Adolf Hitler?
司法部是独立的.
The position of the judge was one of complete independence.
恩
Mm-hm.
那你如何解释
Now would you describe the contrast, if any,
在1933年纳粹上台以后的情况
after the coming to power of National Socialism in 1 933?
法官们要被迫接受一些权力的改变.
Judges became subject to something outside of objective justice.
他们受国家利益支配.
They were subject to what was necessary for the protection of the country.
-你可以解释一下吗?  首先要替法官考虑的是
Would you explain this, please?  The first consideration of the judge
他们没有对抗国会的权力,
became the punishment of acts against the state
rather than objective consideration of the case.
还有什么变化吗?
And what other changes were there?
上诉权也被取消了.
The right to appeal was eliminated.
最高法院被人民特殊法院取代了.
The Supreme Court of the Reich was replaced by peoples' and special courts.
种族概念第一次写入了法律.
The concept of race was made a Iegal concept for the first time.
结果如何?
And what was the result of this?
结果?
The result?
结果是移交了司法部的权力
The result was to hand over the administration of justice
变成了专政
into the hands of the dictatorship.
威克博士....  劳森上校,
Dr Wieck....  Colonel Lawson,
我想问几个问题.
I'd Iike to ask a few questions.
司法部是否有对此提出抗议?
Did the judiciary protest these Iaws abridging their independence?
有一些人提出， 其他的都顺从或被迫顺从了.
A few of them did. Those who did resigned or were forced to resign.
其他的...
Others...
就直接顺应新局势了.
adapted themselves to the new situation.
司法部是否有意识到巨大的转变?
Do you think the judiciary was aware of the consequences to come?
起初或许没有
At first, perhaps not.
后来只要是人就都知道了.
Later it became clear to anyone who had eyes and ears.
谢谢
Thank you.
你可否告诉我们刑法方面的修改.
Now, would you please describe for us the changes in criminal Iaw.
明显的特征是死刑条款增多了.
Its characteristic was an ever-increasing inflation of the death penalty.
只要是波兰人或犹太人
Sentences were passed against defendants
都要受到审判.
just because they were Poles or Jews, or politically undesirable.
纳粹的衡量方法也被引进,
Novel National Socialist measures were introduced,
对人种进行分类.
among them sexual sterilisation for those who were categorised as asocial.
在1935年法官是否需要特别标记?
Was it necessary for judges to wear any distinctive mark on their robes in 1 935?
这就是所谓的 "法萨法案"
The so-called "Fuhrer's decree"
要求法官穿上十字记号的法官袍.
required judges to wear the insignia of the swastika on their robes.
你有佩带吗?  不
Did you wear such an insignia?  No.
我以此为耻.
I would have been ashamed to wear it.
在1935年你是否辞职?  是
Did you resign in 1 935?  Yes, sir.
欧内斯特·姜宁有穿上吗?
Did Ernst Janning wear a swastika on his robe?
是
Yes.
问毕。谢谢
That's all. Thank you.
罗尔福
Herr Rolfe.
Herr Justizrat Dr Wieck.
你刚才提到 "出于保护国家的必要."
You used the phrase "necessary for the protection of the country."
你可以说明一下
Would you explain the conditions in Germany
当时德国的情况吗?
at the time National Socialism came to power?
什么情况?
What conditions?
当时有饥荒?
Would you say there was widespread hunger?
是
Yes.
还有国内的不统一?
Would you say there was internal disunity?
是
Yes.
有共产党吗?  是
Was there a Communist Party?  Yes.
是德国的第三大党吗?
Was it the third Iargest party in Germany?
是
Mm... yes.
你是不是要说纳粹某种程度上拯救了国家?
Would you say that National Socialism helped to cure some of these conditions?
是，但付出了惨重的代价...
Yes, but at a terrible price, and...
请你直接回答问题就可以了.
PIease, confine yourself to answering the questions only.
那么，一个法官如果不穿那样的法官袍
Therefore, was it not possible that a judge might wear a swastika
他是否还有可能继续为他的国家工作?
and yet work for what he thought was best for his country?
不，不可能
No. It was not possible.
Dr Wieck,
据你所说,
you were not in the administration from the years 1 935 to 1 943,
1935 到 1943 年你不在行政部门
by your own admission.
你是否可能知道行政部门被扭曲?
Is it not possible that your view of the administration might be distorted?
不
No, it is not.
那你怎么可以对行政部门作证?
How can you testify about events in the administration if you were not there?
在政府机构我有很多朋友
I had many friends in the Iegal administration.
那里有期刊和书籍
There were journals and books.
期刊和书籍?
From journals and books?
我明白了
I see.
你刚才提到
Dr Wieck, you referred to "novel National Socialist measures introduced,
纳粹的衡量方法被引进
among them sexual sterilisation."
那你是否知道里萨法案不是纳粹原创呢,
Are you aware that sexual sterilisation was not invented by National Socialism,
而是在数年前
but had been advanced for years before as a weapon
针对处理不合格的囚犯制定的?
in dealing with the mentally incompetent and the criminal?
是，我知道
Yes, I am aware of that.
你是否知道这在其他国家也被倡导?
Are you aware it has advocates among Ieading citizens in many countries?
我不是这方面的专家
I am not an expert on such Iaws.
允许我为你读一段.
Then permit me to read one to you.
这是最高法院意见
This is a High Court opinion
这在别国法律中存在.
upholding such Iaws in existence in another country.
我来引用..
And I quote..
"我们不止一次见到社会福利
"We have seen more than once that the public welfare
谋求最高利益."
may call upon their best citizens for their Iives."
"如果是为了整体利益
"It would be strange indeed if it could not call upon
局部的牺牲是可以理解的
those who already sap the strength of the state for these Iesser sacrifices
in order to prevent our being swamped by incompetence."
"对于低能劣等的罪犯
"It is better if, instead of waiting to execute degenerate offspring for crime
or to Iet them starve for their imbecility,
社会应该在第一时间处理他们
society can prevent their propagation by medical means in the first place."
"三代的愚蠢已经足够了."
"Three generations of imbeciles are enough."
现在你想起来了吗，威克博士?  不，没有
Do you recognise it now, Dr Wieck?  No, sir, I don't.
事实上你也不知道,
Actually, there is no particular reason you should,
因为这是引用自,
since the opinion upholds the sterilisation Iaw in the state of Virginia,
美国维吉尼亚法案
of the United States,
美国法理学家
and was written by that great American jurist
奥立弗·温德尔·福尔摩斯
Supreme Court Justice OIiver Wendell Holmes.
Now, Dr Wieck,
从刚才所听到的,
in view of what you have just Iearned,
你是否还要说里萨法案是“纳粹的衡量方法”呢?
can you still say that sexual sterilisation was a "novel National Socialist measure"?
是，可以这么说
Yes, I can say it,
因为这在以前从来没有对政治犯适用过.
because it was never before used as a weapon against political opponents.
你是否有过这样的经历
Do you personally know of a case
处理这样的政治犯?
where someone was sterilised for political reasons?
我知道有这样的事情.  这不是我的问题
I know that such things were done.  That's not the question.
请回答 你是否知道
PIease answer the question. Do you know of a case?
我不知道这样特种的案例
I don't know of any specific case or specific date.
那么你是否有相应的第一手资料!
I am asking if you have any first-hand, personal knowledge of such a case!
不，我没有这方面的知识
No, I have no such personal knowledge.
谢谢
Thank you.
Dr Wieck,
你知道有关对欧内斯特·姜宁的控诉吧?
you are aware of the charges in the indictment against Ernst Janning?
是
Yes, I am.
你认为他是否需要负责?
Can you honestly say he is responsible for them?
是
Yes, I can.
你认为自己没有责任?
Do you consider yourself free of responsibility?
是
Yes, I do.
你是否有在1934年的文职人员誓词中发誓?
Dr Wieck, did you ever swear to the Civil Servant Loyalty Oath of 1 934?
法官大人，我反对
Your Honour, I object.
证人无须回答， 他不是在受审
The witness doesn't have to answer that question. He's not on trial.
全德国都在受审， 当审理欧内斯特·姜宁的时候
AII Germany is on trial. This tribunal put it on trial when it indicted Ernst Janning.
为了寻找责任， 需要扩大范围.
If responsibility is to be found, the widest Iatitude is to be permitted.
反对无效
Objection overruled.
你是否有在1934年的文职人员誓词中发誓?
Did you ever swear to the Civil Servant Loyalty Oath of 1 934?
每个人都发誓了  我们对每个人不感兴趣.
Everyone did.  We are not interested in everyone.
我们只在乎你做的.
We are interested in what you did.
可以读一下1933年3月第三帝国的誓词吗
Would you read the oath from the Reich Law Gazette, March 1 933.
"我发誓效忠人民的领袖：阿道夫·西特勒,
"I swear that I shall obey the Ieader of the German Reich and people, Adolf Hitler,
忠诚于他， 忠诚于法律
that I shall be Ioyal to him, that I will observe the Iaws
我会尽职负责， 所以上帝保佑我们."
and that I will conscientiously fulfil my duties, so help me God."
每个人都发誓了
Everyone swore to it.
这是强制的
It was mandatory.
是
Yes.
但你是个极有远见的人.
But you're such a perceptive man, Dr Wieck. You could see what was coming.
你应该知道纳粹党会给德国带来灾难.
You could see that National Socialism was Ieading Germany to disaster.
"是人都知道"
"It was clear to anyone who had eyes and ears."
你难道不知道那意味着什么
Didn't you realise what it would have meant
如果你，还有其他人民都拒绝发誓?
if you, and men Iike you, would have refused to swear to the oath?
那么西特勒就没有可能掌权!
It would have meant that Hitler could never have come to absolute power!
你为什么不这么做呢，威克博士？
Why didn't you? Dr Wieck, why didn't you?
你可以给我们一个解释吗?
Can you give us an explanation?
是否这样同你的退休金有关呢?
Has it something to do with your pension?
难道那比你的国家还重要?
Did it mean more to you than your country?
法官大人， 我反对这一系列的提问
Your Honour, I object to the entire Iine of questioning
应该从记录中删除.
and ask that it be stricken from the record.
检查团不就是为了追究责任吗.
Prosecuting counsel's job is to find responsibility.
法官大人，我反对
Your Honour, I made an objection.
公诉人不要追究责任?
Prosecution does not want to find responsibility?
这里必要谈效忠誓言!
There is responsibility for more here than swearing to a Ioyalty oath!
大有必要!
There is indeed!
遵守秩序
Order.  One thing even the German machine,
with its monumental efficiency, has been unable to destroy!
Order!  AII the victims!
全世界的受害者都知道...
More victims than the world has ever known. They will walk in here...
遵守秩序!
Order! Order!
法官席会听取双方意见， 但是我实在无法容忍.
This tribunal will admonish both counsels. It will not tolerate this again.
我们不是要你们发火， 我们在寻求正义
We're not here to Iisten to such outbursts, but to serve justice.
法官大人，我反对.  反对无效
Your Honour, I made an objection.  The objection is overruled.
证人离席
The witness is excused.
读过姜宁的书吗?  没有.
Ever read any books by Janning?  No, I don't think so.
法律的意义.  怎么？有意思吗?
The Meaning of the Law.  How is it? Interesting?
姜宁的书都很有意思.
AII the books by Janning are interesting.
他反映的是一个时代的激情和希望
They're a picture of an era, its hopes, aspirations.
和我们没有太大区别
They weren't very different from ours.
听这段评价魏玛宪法的
Listen to this, on the signing of the Weimar constitution.
"现在我们可以展望没有战火的德国"
"Now we can Iook forward to a Germany without guns and bloodshed."
"我们可以不用死亡"
"A Germany of justice, where men can Iive instead of die."
"有自由和人性的德国"
"A Germany of purpose, of freedom, of humanity."
"A Germany that calls for the best in man."
能写出这样的书的人
How could a man who wrote words Iike these
他怎么可能会是杀人犯呢?
be part of sterilisations and murders? How could he be?
丹， 这里发生的很多事情都让人不明白的.
Dan, there are a Iot of things that happened here that nobody understands.
我知道
I know.
但是检查团还是要证明他们的控诉的
But the prosecution is going to have to prove every inch of its allegation
我也还是要对他做出宣判
against a man Iike Janning if I'm to pronounce sentence on him.
先生们，我要走了
Gentlemen, I'm on my way.
走吗，肯?  好
Coming, Ken?  Right.
There's just this business on the curtailment of rights.
明天
Tomorrow.
丹， 我太太要办个聚会.
Dan, my wife is planning a get-together tomorrow at the Grand Hotel.
她希望你能来.  好的，谢谢
She wants you to come.  AII right. Thank you.
她还想给你介绍女伴呢
And she'd Iike to provide you with some kind of female companionship.
她觉得你可能太孤单了
She thought you might be Ionely here.
不，谢谢
No, thanks, Curtiss. Thanks very much.
你知道太太们总喜欢给人配对
You know how these wives Iove to play Cupid.
我想最好还是单身  好的
I think I'II keep it stag.  AII right.
你怎么样，肯?  谢谢，我和太太已经够忙了
How about you, Ken?  Thanks. My wife and I are busy.
晚安  晚安，丹.
Good night.  Good night, Dan.
海尔柏斯德夫人, 我能不能...
Mrs Halbestadt, could I...
Hello.
法官大人，这是柏荷特夫人
Your Honour, this is Madame Bertholt.
这是海伍德法官
This is His Honour, Judge Haywood.
柏荷特夫人,这是她的房子
Madame Bertholt, this is her house.
她是来地下室拿些东西.
She came to get some of her belongings from the basement.
我不知道她今晚会来.  这是我该做的.
I didn't know she was coming tonight.  It's my responsibility, Mrs Halbestadt.
我在没有找到大房子以前把东西放这了.
I've stored some of my things here until I could get a room Iarge enough for them.
我希望你不要介意  不，一点也不
I hope you don't mind.  No. Not at all.
要是你愿意， 你可以检查一下
You can examine what I have here if you Iike.
当然不用  那我取走了
Of course not.  Then I'II just take these out.
谢谢  让我来帮你
Thank you, Mrs Halbestadt.  Let me help you.
我可以的  我只是要拿出去
I can manage.  I'II just take it outside. PIease.
晚安
Good night.
很重吧，都是些无关紧要的书和图画， 但对我很重要.
It's heavy. It's full of books and pictures that mean nothing to anyone but me.
Mr Schmidt!  Your Honour.
可以载柏荷特夫人回家吗?  是的，法官大人
Would you drive Mrs Bertholt home?  Yes, Your Honour.
我希望你在这过的愉快.  是，非常愉快
I hope you're comfortable here.  Yes, I am. Very.
我最喜欢的地方还是花园
My favourite spot was always the garden.
提醒海尔柏斯德夫人照看好假山花园.
Remind Mr Halbestadt to take good care of the rock garden.
在夏天你会获得很多乐趣的.
You'II get a great deal of pleasure out of it in summer.
我坐在前面，谢谢
I'II sit in front, thank you.
晚安  晚安
Good night.  Good night.
开罗街 1 1 5.  是，夫人
Karolinenstrasse 1 1 5.  Yes, madam.
(whispered conversation)
坐下，坐下
Sit down, sit down.
海尔柏斯德夫人, 你为柏斯德夫人工作不是吗?
Mrs Halbestadt, you worked for Mrs Bertholt, didn't you?
是的，法官大人  她住在这多久了?
Yes, Your Honour.  How Iong did she Iive here?
柏斯德夫人?
Madame Bertholt?
噢，她们世代都住在这里.
Oh, Madame Bertholt and her family have Iived here for many generations.
谢谢
Thank you.
法官大人， 你来有什么事情?
Your Honour, you came in here for something?
是
Oh! Oh, yeah.
我想做一份三明治.
I'm just going to make myself a sandwich.
我们来做吧， 做任何你想要的.
We will make it. We will make you anything you want.
不，小事 我总是回家后自己动手做.
No, it's nothing. I always did it for myself back home.
你想要什么口味的? 我有火腿、奶酪等.
What would you Iike? I have some ham and cheese and Iiverwurst.
奶酪好了
Cheese will be fine.
你真是太好了
That's very kind of you.
海尔柏斯德先生， 生活在纳粹之下是怎么样种感觉呢?
Mr Halbestadt, what was it Iike, Iiving under National Socialism?
什么感觉?  对，我是说：天天都要面对?
What was it Iike?  Yes. I mean, uh... day-to-day?
我知道很多像你们这样的人.
I know many people at home Iike you.
我相信你们是好人
You're good people. I believe that.
那么生活在西特勒统治下是什么感觉呢?
What was it Iike for you, Iiving under Hitler?
我和我丈夫都不是政治分子.
We were not political. Mr Halbestadt and I are not political.
Ein Glas fur die Milch, bitte.  Ja.
不，但你们一定清楚当时发生了什么事情.
No, but you must have been aware of some of the events that were going on.
很多事情都在发生
Many things were going on, Mr Halbestadt.
有游行
There were parades.
西特勒每年都会参加的
Hitler and Goebbels came here every year.
场面如何呢?
What was it Iike?
我们从来没有参加集会
We never attended meetings. Never.
我不是要审判你们 我只是...
I'm not trying to put you on trial. I'm just, uh...
我只是好奇，想知道而已.
I'm just curious. I'd Iike to know.
法官大人，你的三明治.  谢谢
Here's your sandwich, Your Honour.  Thank you.
别客气
You're welcome.
谢谢
Thank you.
比方说，这附近有个地方叫达靠的.
For instance, there was a place called Dachau not too many miles from here.
你们知道那里发生了什么吗?
Did you ever know what was going on there?
我们什么都不知道.
We knew nothing about it. Nothing about it.
你怎么可以问我们是否知道呢?
How can you ask if we know anything about that?
对不起
I'm sorry.
法官大人， 我们只是小人物.
Your Honour, we are only Iittle people.
我们在军队里散失了儿子
We Iost a son in the army
女儿也被炸死了
and our daughter in the bombing.
战争时我们几乎饿死了.
During the war we almost starved.
对我们来说很可怕.
It was terrible for us.
我相信也是如此
I'm sure it was.
西特勒... 西特勒也做了一些好事.
Hitler... Hitler did some good things.
我不会说他没有做什么好事.
I won't say he didn't do some good things.
他建造了告诉公路， 给了更多人就业机会.
He built the autobahn. He gave more people work.
我不会说他没有做什么好事.
We won't say he didn't do some good things.
但其他的事情...
But the other things...
别人说的他对犹太人还有其他人做了什么， 我们都不知道.
The things they say he did to the Jews and the rest, we knew nothing about that.
很少德国人知道.
Very few Germans did.
如果我们知道...
And if we did know...
我们能做什么呢?
what could we do?
但你夫人说你什么都不知道
But Mrs Halbestadt said you didn't know.
柏斯德夫人对此有什么反映吗?
Mrs Bertholt, how did she react to all this?
柏斯德夫人是很好的人.
Ah, Madame Bertholt is a very fine woman, Your Honour.
我相信如此， 那她丈夫呢?
I'm sure she is. What about her husband?
他是军人
He was in the army.
他发生了什么事情?
What happened to him?
他是麦尔迪一案中的被告.
He was one of the defendants in the Malmedy case.
柏斯德将军. 卡尔·柏斯德.
General Bertholt. Karl Bertholt.
他被处死刑了，法官大人.
He was executed, Your Honour.
是，我知道
Yes, I know that.
接下来是摄影师鲁道夫·楞次的资料
The document then states that the photographer Rudolf Lenz
他被要求在两星期内
is requested to present himself within two weeks
到医院接受“治疗”
at one of the hospitals mentioned below for "medical treatment".
接下来公诉人还会提供 宣誓证书488#,
Next, prosecution presents affidavit document no.488,
同女裁缝安尼相关
which concerns the seamstress Anni Munch.
文档内容如下:
Document reads as follows:
"地方法院富兰克林做出如下决定:
"District court Frankfurt am Main has decided the following:
女裁缝安尼有恶疾."
the seamstress Anni Munch, daughter of Wilhelm Munch, is to be sterilised."
"她被要求在两星期内
"She is requested to present herself within two weeks
到以下指定医院接受治疗."
at one of the hospitals mentioned below."
"如果她不愿前往， 将强制执行."
"If she does not take herself voluntarily, she will be taken by force."
接下来文件449#,
Next, document no.449, interrogatories in the German and English text,
是农场帮工沫尔的资料.
concerning the farmer's helper Meyer Eichinger.
法官大人  什么?
Your Honour.  What?
被告对这些反复性的证据材料表示反对.
Defence objects to introduction of these repetitive documents.
根据初审的决议,
According to the ruling of the first tribunal,
这些材料都是不可接纳的
such documents are not even admissible
除非有独立的证据证明它们的真实性.
unless supported by independent evidence of their authenticity.
反对有效.
Objection sustained.
法官大人， 可以问被告一个问题吗?
Your Honour, may I ask the defence a question?
是
Yes.
如果有证人的话证据是否成立呢?
Would evidence on sterilisation be admissible if there were a witness?
是  谢谢.
Yes.  Thank you.
公诉人传召证人鲁道夫·皮特斯出庭作证
Prosecution calls the witness Rudolf Petersen.
请举右手?
Will you raise your right hand?
我向全能的主宣誓
I swear by God the AImighty and Omniscient
我会说出事实的真相， 毫无虚假.
that I will speak the pure truth and withhold and add nothing.
是，我会
Yes, I do.
你可否告诉法庭你的全名以及住所.
Will you please tell the court your full name and place of residence.
鲁道夫·皮特斯·富兰克 格兰特街
Rudolf Petersen. Frankfurt am Main. Gretweg, Nummer sieben.
你何时出生，皮特斯?
When were you born, Mr Petersen?
1914年05月20日.
May 20, 1 91 4.
你的职业是?
And what is your occupation?
贝克的帮手
Baker's helper. I'm a baker's helper.
你父母还在世吗?
Are your parents Iiving?
不
No.
他们的死因是什么?
What were the causes of their deaths?
皮特斯先生, 他们是自然死亡吗?
Mr Petersen, did they die of natural causes?
是，是， 自然死亡.
Ja, ja. Ja. Natural.
你父亲是属于什么政党?
Now, Mr Petersen, what political party did your father belong to?
共产党.
Communist. The Communist Party.
Uh-huh.
现在想想
Now, think back.
记得在1933年纳粹上台以前
Do you remember anything unusual that happened to you and your family in 1933,
发生了什么不寻常的事情吗?
before the Nazis came to power?
我是说暴力的行为.
I mean anything of a violent nature.
是
Ja, ja.
你当时几岁?  1 9.
How old were you at the time?  1 9.
你可以告诉法庭当时的情况吗?
Would you please tell the court what happened?
噢，一些……
Uh... some...
一些SA闯入了我们的房子
Some SA men broke into the house, our house,
砸坏了窗户和门.
and they broke the windows and the door.
他们说我们是叛国者
They called us traitors
他们还想打我的父亲.
and they tried to... to beat up my father.
接下来如何?
And what happened then?
我和兄弟就去帮忙
My brothers and I, we went to help him.
然后就有一场打斗
And there was a fight.
最后我们把他们赶到了街上
Finally we got them outside in the street
我们痛扁了他们一顿,
and we beat them up,
然后扭送他们到警察局.
and turned them over to the police.
警察有采取什么行动吗?  没有
Did the police do anything about it?  No.
为什么不?
Why not?
当时正是国家大选.
It was then at the time of the national elections.
纳粹党当权了吗?  是
The National Socialists came to power?  Ja.
听着，皮特斯先生
Now, Mr Petersen,
在1933年纳粹上台以后又发生了什么事情?
what happened after 1 933, after the Nazis came to power?
我在农场找到了一份工作,
I got a job on a farm,
为了工作， 驾驶卡车是必要的.
but for the work, to drive a truck it was necessary.
我到了市府办理证件.
I went to the city building to apply for a Iicence.
然后又怎么了?
And what happened there?
他们带我见一名官员.
They took me to an official.
你以前在那里办过手续吗?
Did you ever have any dealings with this official before?
他就是那天晚上和我们打架的人之一.
He was one of the men who broke into our house that night.
对于你的申请他说什么?
What did he say to your application?
他说需要一份检查.
He said an examination there would have to be.
到哪里检查?
Where was the examination to take place?
在斯图加特地方法院.
In the district court of Stuttgart.
谁是主审法官?
Who was the presiding justice in the court?
霍夫斯特法官.
Justice Hofstetter.
庭上发生了什么情况?
Now, what happened in the courtroom?
他们问我的全名之类.
They asked me my full name and so forth.
他们还问你什么?
What else did they ask you?
他们问我西特勒什么时候出生的.
They asked me when Adolf Hitler and Dr Goebbels were born.
你怎么回答?
What did you reply?
我说我不知道， 也不在乎.
I told them I didn't know, and also that I didn't care.
(laughter)
他们还有问你问题吗?
Did they ask you any more questions?
不， 他们告诉我十天内会有消息.
No. They told me that I would be hearing from them in ten days.
我明白了
I see.
Mr Petersen,
我想让你看些东西
I'd Iike you to Iook at something.
记得吗?  是
Do you recognise it?  Ja.
你可以当庭读出来吗?
Would you please read it for the tribunal?
"斯图加特地方法院."
"District court of Stuttgart."
"面包师鲁道夫·皮特斯, 出生于1914年05月20日,
"The baker Rudolf Petersen, born May 20th 1 91 4,
铁路职工汉斯·皮特斯之子,
son of railway employee Hans Petersen,
被判种族低劣."
is to be sterilised."
能否请你读最后一段?
(Lawson) Would you read the Iast paragraph?
"因此建议他在两周内
"It is therefore requested he present himself within two weeks
到以下指定医院接受治疗"
to one of the hospitals mentioned below."
"如果他不自愿前往,
"If he does not betake himself voluntarily,
他将被强制执行."
he will be taken by force."
现在请念出底下的签名.
Now please read the signature at the bottom.
"主审法官霍夫斯特."
"Presiding Justice Hofstetter."
再读下面的签名?
Would you read what is written below the signature?
下面?  下面.
Below?  (Lawson) Below.
"权威认证：欧内斯特·姜宁,
"By authority of Ernst Janning,
司法部长."
Minister of Justice."
法官大人,
Your Honour,
被告可以看皮特斯的文件资料吗?
may the defence see the file of Mr Petersen?
你收到裁决书后如何?
What did you do after you received the Ietter, Mr Petersen?
我逃跑了， 躲在一个农场朋友的家里.
I ran away. I stayed at the farm of a friend I have.
你回来了吗?
And did you return?
我怎么?  你回去了吗?
Did I what?  Did you return?
是
Yes.
又发生了什么?
And what happened then?
警察来了.
The police came. The police came.
他们把你带去哪里?  医院
Where did they take you?  (quietly) To the hospital.
皮特斯先生， 能否请你发言大声点.
Mr Petersen. Excuse me, I wonder if you could speak a Iittle Iouder, please.
去医院
To the hospital.
医院里发生了什么?  他们把我关在那.
What happened at the hospital?  They kept me there.
护士...
The nurse who was...
最后还是进来了.
Well, she came in anyway.
她为我准备手术.
She was to prepare me for the operation.
她说整件事情都很可怕.
And she said she thought the whole thing was terrible.
然后医生就进来了， 准备...
And then the doctor came in, who was supposed to do the...
他说也觉得很恶心
and he said he thought it was awful.
你是否劣等种族?
Were you in fact sterilised?
谢谢，皮特斯先生.
(Lawson) Thank you very much, Mr Petersen.
问毕
That's all.
罗尔福发言.
Herr Rolfe.
Mr Petersen,
如果你愿意， 你现在可以取下耳机.
you may take your earphones off now, if you want to.
你说你是面包师贝克的助手?
Mr Petersen, you say you work as a baker's helper? Is that correct?
是，没错
Yes, that is right.
你还有其他什么职业?
What other occupations have you held?
我为父亲工作
I have worked for my father.
你父亲职业?  铁路职工.
What did your father do?  He was a railroad worker.
是，他具体工作是什么?
Yes, but what did he do?
他负责十字路口栅栏的升降.
He would raise and Iower the barrier at the crossing for traffic.
你也提到了你的兄弟
And you spoke about your brothers.
你有多少个兄弟?  五个
How many brothers do you have?  Five.
姐妹呢?  四个
And sisters?  Four.
就是说十口之家了? -是
Then you are a family of ten?  Yes.
你兄弟的职业?
What occupations do your brothers have?
劳工
Labourers.
都是劳工?
AII Iabourers?
我知道了
I see.
你说斯图加特法院问了你两个问题,
Mr Petersen, you said the court at Stuttgart asked you two questions,
西特勒的生日.
the birth dates of Hitler and Dr Goebbels.
对吗?  没错
Is that correct?  Yes. Correct.
他们还问你什么?
What else did they ask you?
恩
Uh...
没有了.
Nothing else.
你确定?
Are you sure?
你确定没有问到你学业的问题?
Are you sure there were no questions about your schooling?
反对!
(Lawson) Objection!
证人早已回答问题了.
The witness has already answered that question.
反对有效
Objection sustained.
我可以问你吗，皮特斯...
May I ask you, Mr Petersen...
我可以问你...
may I ask you...
你读了几年书?
how Iong did you attend school?
六年  六年，为什么不久些?
Six years.  Six years. Why not Ionger?
我必须工作
I had to go to work.
你觉得自己在学校是否很聪明?
Would you consider yourself a very bright fellow at school?
学校? 说起来...
School? It was...
这已经是很久远的事了， 我...
It was a Iong while ago. I don't...
或许是因为你跟不上其他孩子
Perhaps you were not able to keep up with the others
所以你辍学了?
and that's why you did not continue?
反对，法官大人
Objection, Your Honour.
证人的学业同发生在他身上的事情无关
The witness' school record has no bearing on what happened to him.
健康法院的职责就是检场智力.
It was the task of the health court to sterilise the mentally incompetent.
反对无效.
Objection overruled.
你是否能够跟上其他人的学习进度?
Were you able or were you not able to keep up with the others?
我不得不提到学校有关皮特斯学习效率的报告.
I would Iike to refer to the efficiency report from the school about Mr Petersen.
他无法进步， 只好分配到了后进班.
He failed to be promoted and was placed in a class of backward children.
你说你父母死于自然.
You say your parents died of natural causes.
是
Yes.
你能否仔细描述你母亲死于什么疾病?
Would you describe in detail the illness your mother died of?
她死于心脏病
She died of her heart.
在她临时的阶段...
In the Iast stages of her illness, did your mother show any...
她是否精神方面有异常?
mental peculiarities?
精神... 不，不
Mental... No. No.
从斯图加特来的报告显示,
In the decision that came from Stuttgart,
你母亲承袭了遗传的低能症.
it is stated that your mother suffered from hereditary feeble-mindedness.
这不是……不是真的.
That is not... That is not true.
不是真的，不是
Not true, not true.
你是否可以澄清
Can you give us some clarification as to how
为什么斯图加特法院会做出那样的决定?
the Hereditary Health Court in Stuttgart arrived at that decision?
这只是他们自己捏造的理由， 将我送上了手术台.
It was just something they said to put me on the operating table.
只是他们捏造的?  是!
It was just something they said?  Yes!
在健康法院的检查中
Mr Petersen, there was a simple test that the Health Court used to ask
有一个常用的检查智力发育完整与否的测验
in all cases of mental incompetence.
既然你说他们没有问,
Since you say they did not ask you then,
或许现在你可以回答了?
perhaps you can answer it for us now?
从一组词中 "hare", "hunter", "field".
Form a sentence out of the words "hare", "hunter", "field".
法官大人，反对
Your Honour! Objection!
Mr Petersen,
斯图加特法院当时是否有这样的做法?
was the court in Stuttgart constituted Iike this one?
我不明白...
I don't understand what...
当时有听众吗?
Was there an audience?
听众? 是的
An audience? Yes, yes.
谢谢
Thank you.
反对无效
Objection overruled.
Hare, hunter, field, 皮特斯先生.
Hare, hunter, field, Mr Petersen.
慢慢来.
Take your time.
Hare, hunter, field. 恩...
Hare, hunter, field. Uh...
Hare,
hunter...
他们早已...
They had already made up...
当我进入法庭时， 他们早已拿定主意.
When I walked into the court, they had made up their minds.
他们早已拿定主意!
They had made up their minds!
他们像对待囚犯一样把我送到医院.
They put me in the hospital, Iike a criminal.
我什么都不好说. 我...
I could not say anything, I could not do anything. I...
我只好在那撒谎.
I had to Iie there.
我... 我的母亲...
My... my mother...
你说她什么.
what you say about her.
她是个女人, 一个勤劳工作的女仆
She was a woman, a servant woman, who worked hard.
她是个努力工作的人.
She was a hardworking woman.
你说的一切，很不公平.
And it is not fair  not fair  what you say.
我有
I have it here.
我给你们看她的照片
I want to show you. I have here her picture.
我想让你们看看
I would Iike you Iooked at it.
我想让你们来评判
I would Iike you to judge.
我想要你告诉我
I want that you tell me,
她是低能的吗?
was she feeble-minded?
我的母亲!
My mother!
她是低能的吗?
Was she feeble-minded?
她是吗?
Was she?
我觉得我有必要向法庭指出
I feel it is my duty to point out to the tribunal
证人现在情绪失控.
that the witness is not in control of his mental processes.
我知道我没有
I know I'm not.
从那天开始,
Since that day,
我就变成原来的一半.
I've been half I've ever been.
法庭并不知道你当时如何.
The tribunal does not know how you were before.
这永远也不可能知道， 现在只有你的证词.
It can never know. It has only your word.
现在休庭.
Court is adjourned.
(# dance band)
检查团真是让人头疼 -
That's one problem we have with the prosecution -
里面总是有像劳森这样的激进分子.
it's filled with young radicals Iike Lawson.
劳森是这样的吗? 激进分子?
Is that what Lawson is? A young radical?
当然，他是FDR的培养人之一.
Well, he was a personal protege of FDR.
FDR也有些非激进的吧，不是吗?
FDR had a few friends who weren't radicals, didn't he?
说一个.
Name one.
温德尔·威尔忌.  威尔忌.
Wendell Wilkie.  Wilkie.
他是你心中理想的保守派?
Is he your idea of a conservative?
事实上，丹， 我真的不知道你的立场如何?
As a matter of fact, Dan, I've been wondering how you stand?
那我现在就说明， 我是忠实的共和党派
I'II clarify that for you, Curtiss. I'm a rock-ribbed Republican
觉得富兰克林·罗斯福是个伟人.
who thought that Franklin Roosevelt was a great man.
哦，这样
Oh. One of those.
马克斯!
Max!
你认识他吗?  不认识
Max Perkins. Do you know him?  I don't think so.
他是联合出版社的
He's with the United Press.
马克斯，你在这干吗?  我以为你又要起哄了.
Max, what are you doing here?  I thought you might kick up a row.
我可没有喝那么多
I haven't had that much to drink.
哦，对不起，这是艾夫斯法官  你好
Oh, I'm sorry. This is Judge Ives.  Hello.
艾夫斯夫人.  你好?
Mrs Ives.  How do you do?
你好?  海伍德法官，柏斯德夫人.
How do you do?  Judge Haywood, Mrs Bertholt.
我们见过面了.  是
We have met.  Yes, we have.
为什么不一起来喝一杯呢?  非常乐意.
Won't you join us for a drink?  We would Iike to very much.
马克斯，你坐这好了?  谢谢
Max, will you sit here?  Thank you.
对了，马克斯， 我特别喜欢你写的有关柏斯德夫人的文章.
Incidentally, Max, I admired your article on Mrs Bertholt very much.
那是直接报道， 柏斯德为她丈夫的辩护很精彩.
It was straight reporting. Her defence of her husband was quite eloquent.
你是否要对这些审判做报道?
Are you going to do a story on these trials?
说实话吧，法官.
I'II tell you something frankly, Judge.
我现在不能报道纽伦堡的案子.
At the moment I couldn't give a story away on the Nuremberg trials.
什么意思?  美国报社不感兴趣.
What do you mean, Mr Perkins?  The American public isn't interested.
战争才两年时间.
The war's only been over two years, Mr Perkins.
对
That's right.
可以点酒了吗?  看看我们还需要什么.
May I take your order?  Yes. See what the Iadies will have.
丹，再来点啤酒怎么样?  不，啤酒我喝够了.
How about some more beer, Dan?  No, I think I've had my fill of beer.
如果可以，我想试试别的.
I'd Iike to try something else, if I may.
为什么不尝尝苏格拉冰呢? 这是当地的酒
Why don't you try some Sonnenberg or Schwalbenwinkel? It's the Iocal wine.
苏格拉冰?  苏格拉冰.
Sonnenberg or...?  Schwalbenwinkel.
是的，我想要点苏格拉冰.
Yes, I think I'd Iike that. Some Schwalbenwinkel.
你要吗?  是的，谢谢
Will you have some?  Yes, thank you.
我们还是要啤酒吗，马克斯?  好
Shall we stay with the beer, Max?  Fine.
谢谢
Thank you.
那晚你顺利回去了吧?  是的，谢谢
You got home all right the other night?  Yes, thank you.
我真不知道没有车我该怎么办.
I don't know what I would have done without the car.
柏斯德夫人， 你的英语讲的真好.
You speak English very well, Mrs Bertholt.
谢谢
Thank you.
我和丈夫在美国待了两年
My husband and I spent two years in America.
我希望你有空可以参观一下纽伦堡.
I hope you've had a chance to see something of Nuremberg.
我想那可能会影响法官的公正.
I'm afraid mainly the road between my house and the Palace of Justice.
或许有些地方， 从历史学的角度来看对案件有帮助.
And then some places that have to do with the case, historical aspects.
从纳粹角度， 你应该从另一个角度看纽伦堡.
The Nazi aspects. You should see some of the other parts of Nuremberg.
在旧城区有很多好看的,
There are many beautiful things to see in the old part of town,
比如重建的博物馆.
museums we're trying to rebuild.
还有在老歌剧院的钢琴音乐会.
And there's a concert, a piano concert, next week at the old opera house.
亚瑟·里斯. 他早前为西特勒演出
Arthur Reiss. He was a refugee from Hitler in the early days.
我们劝服他回来 我想今晚会很精彩.
We've persuaded him to come back. It ought to be quite an evening.
你会来吗?  是，我会
Would you Iike to come?  Yes, I would.
我会让票房给你留张票的， 我是在委员会的.
I'II have them Ieave a ticket for you at the box office. I'm on the committee.
非常感谢，柏斯德夫人.  没什么
Thank you very much, Mrs Bertholt.  It's nothing.
我同美国有个协议 马克斯可以告诉你.
I have a mission with the Americans, as Mr Perkins can tell you.
哦，什么?
Oh? What is that?
使你相信我们并不都是怪物.
To convince you that we're not all monsters.
晚上好, 上校.
Good evening, Colonel.  Colonel, Major Radnitz.
晚上好, 柏斯德夫人.
Good evening, Mrs Bertholt.
我希望你原谅.  可你才来.
I hope you'II excuse me.  You've just come.
不，我必须走了 请见谅.
No, I must go. PIease excuse me.
真是非常愉快的碰面.
It was awfully nice meeting you.
我会在票房给你留票的.
There will be a concert ticket for you at the box office.
谢谢
Thank you.
晚安  晚安
Good night.  Good night.
晚安 -晚安，柏斯德夫人.
Good night.  Good night, Mrs Bertholt.
Huh.
柏斯德夫人对我恨之入骨啊.
Mrs Bertholt doesn't hold a burning passion for me.
我控诉了她丈夫
I prosecuted her husband.
今天看来
Many people think a death sentence would not have been passed
很多人觉得柏斯德将军审判是不会通过死刑的
against General Bertholt today.
我知道.
I'm sure they do.
我也知道今天在纽伦堡
I'm sure there are people who think
他们觉得在席的被告都会无罪
all the prisoners in Nuremberg should be free today.
所有人!
AII of them! Let's...
对不起
Excuse me.
我...
I've had, uh...
我想我喝太多了， 所以失礼了.
I've had one or two too many, as might be painfully obvious to you gentlemen.
今天下午的展览会让我迟到了.
The spectacle this afternoon with Mr Petersen put me off my feed. I'm sorry.
酒来了.
Three beers and Schwalbenwinkel, please.
Prosit. Prosit.
Schwalbenwinkel.  Schwalbenwinkel.
啤酒不错， 他们的手艺真的不错.
Yes, it's good beer. They make it good in this country.
你知道...
You know...
你知道美国人.
You know, there's one thing about Americans.
我们并不是占领者.
We're not cut out to be occupiers.
我们对这里还很不熟悉.
We're new at it and we're not very good at it.
我们来到这里， 看到了什么呢?
We come over here, and what do we see?
我们见到了这个美丽的国家.
We see this beautiful country.
非常美丽
It is beautiful. It's very beautiful.
我们看到了几百年前的文化.
We see the culture that goes back for hundreds of years.
我们见到了亲善的魅力
We see its gemutlich charm,
再如柏斯德夫人这样的美人.
and the charm of people Iike, uh... Mrs Bertholt.
我们有一定的自卑情绪.
We got a built-in inferiority complex.
我们很善忘和宽恕.
We forgive and forget easy.
我们给予另一个值得怀疑的人利益. 这是美国作风
We give the other guy the benefit of the doubt  that's the American way.
我们击败了战争机器（德国）
We beat the greatest war machine since AIexander the Great
现在已经控制了它.
and now the boy scouts take over.
上校，你的问题是， 你要控诉整个国家.
The trouble with you, Colonel, is you'd Iike to indict the whole country.
那或许可以让你情绪上得到满足,
That might be emotionally satisfying to you,
但这不实际， 也不公平.
but it wouldn't be exactly practical, and hardly fair.
几乎不公平?
Hardly fair?
"Hare"（野兔）,
"Hare",
"hunter"（猎人）,
"hunter",
"field"（原野）.
"field".
好的，让我们公平点.
That's right, Iet's be fair.
野兔在原野上被猎人捕获.
The hare was shot by the hunter in the field.
真的很简单.
It's really quite simple.
恩...
Uh...
上校，我想我们该走了.
Colonel, I think we ought to be going.
是的， 我们不该讨论这个.
Yes. We shouldn't be discussing this.
不，法官 我们是公平的美国人
Oh, no, Judge(!) We're fair Americans, and true blue.
我们不会违反秩序的.
We mustn't do anything that's out of order.
我们不能做违反秩序的事情.
We can't do anything that's out of order.
难道你不知道在德国没有纳粹吗，法官?
There are no Nazis in Germany. Didn't you know that, Judge?
爱斯基摩人侵略了德国.
The Eskimos invaded Germany and took over.
所以发生了这么多可怕的事情.
That's how all those terrible things happened.
这不是德国人的错， 都是该死的爱斯基摩人的错!
It wasn't the fault of the Germans, it was the fault of those damn Eskimos!
对不起，对不起
Excuse me. Excuse me.
晚安, 上校.  晚安
Good night, Colonel.  Good night.
(music stops)
大家听我说? 抱歉打扰大家跳舞.
Can I have your attention? Sorry to interrupt your dancing.
以下官员马上向原单位报告.
The following officers are requested to report to their units.
麦卡犀少校, 卡腾少校,
Major McCarthy, Major Citron, Major Cantor,
柏尔斯少尉, 康氖尔少尉,
Captain Byers, Captain Connell,
道古拉斯少尉, 赖斯少校
Captain Douglas, Captain Wolfe, Major Booth and Major Rice.
谢谢，你们可以继续了
Thank you. You can continue dancing.
(music starts)
哈里，什么事情?  俄军在捷克斯洛伐克.
Harry! What is it?  The Russians are in Czechoslovakia.
我们要派遣部队过去.
Masaryk may have committed suicide. We're sending some units over.
你猜会怎么样?
(lves) What do you think will happen?
我不知道
I don't know, sir.
海伍德法官
Oh, Judge Haywood.
艾乐·歇伏
EIsa Scheffler.
晚上好
Guten Abend.
"杜鲁门总统对延长军事训练做出反映."
"President Truman responded by calling for an extension of military training."
"他深深感觉到西方国家的独立
"He stated that he is deeply concerned with the survival of the Western nations
面临着来自东方的威胁."
in face of the threat from the east."
"东方的威胁."
"Threat from the east."
欧内·姜宁， 你听到新闻了吗?
Herr Janning, did you hear what is in the paper?
正同西特勒所说一样: "西方和东方生存的冲突（两大阵营）."
Exactly what Hitler said: "The clash for survival between east and west."
他早就预料了!
Ah, he knew. He knew!
他们会明白我们为什么一直这么做.
They'II see that we knew exactly what we were doing all the time.
他们不能再把我们做囚犯， 而要求我们来帮助.
They cannot call us criminals and at the same time ask us to help them.
我们必须团结， 关键时刻来了.
We must stand together now. The most crucial part of this case is coming up.
爱米尔·哈恩， 我们的快乐时光已经结束了.
We have fallen on happy times, Herr Hahn.
以前你当然可以了
In the old times it would have made your day
if I deigned to say "Good morning" to you.
现在我们都身处牢狱
Now that we are here in this place together,
你也不用多说什么了.
you feel obliged to tell me what to do with my Iife.
欧内·姜宁， 你必须同我们同一阵线.
Herr Janning, you must stand with us.
德国人不好内讧的， 我们有共同的目标
It is not good for Germans to turn on one another. We have a common ground now.
听着
Listen to me, Herr Hahn.
可怕的事情已经发生在我身上了.
Terrible things have happened to me in my Iife.
但最糟糕的事情就是
But the worst thing that has ever happened
我发现与你们这样的人一起.
is to find myself in the company of men Iike you.
我同你们以及你们的政党都没有关系.
I have nothing in common with you and the party hacks.
你和我们有共同点， 我们都是在同一政体下.
You have something in common  you were part of the same regime.
你像我们一样.
You stood by that regime, Iike the rest of us.
还有一点:
And there is something else you have in common:
你也是德国人
you are a German.
(# "Piano Sonata No.8" by Beethoven)
晚上好，你喜欢吗?  是的，非常喜欢
Good evening. Did you Iike it?  Yes, I did. Very much indeed.
我载你吗?  我就住附近.
Can I drop you?  I only Iive a few blocks from here.
我走过去就行了. 要一起散步吗?
I was going to walk. Would you Iike to go for a walk?
好的
Yes. Yes, I would.
我不用车了， 我同柏斯德夫人散步.
I won't need the car now. I'II walk with Mrs Bertholt.
我要等你吗?  不，不
Shall I wait for you?  No, no.
法官大人，我会等你.
I'II wait for you, Your Honour.
(# men sing "Lili Marleen")
# Vor einem groBen Tor
# Steht' ne Laterne
# Und steht sie noch davor
# Da wollen wir uns wiederseh'n
# Bei der Laterne woll'n wir steh'n
# Wie einst Lili Marleen
# Wie einst...
不管情况如何， 德国人总爱唱歌
The German people Iove to sing, no matter what the situation.
我注意到了
I've noticed that.
美国人也常在酒吧唱歌吗？ 我忘了.
Do American people sing in bars, too? I've forgotten.
不，我们是很沉闷的.
No. We're apt to be pretty sullen in bars.
# Und alle Leute soll'n es seh'n
# Wenn wir...
我希望你能了解德国
I wish you understood German.
语言很美，很忧伤
The words are very beautiful. Very sad.
比英语要忧伤多了
Much sadder than the English words.
"德国军人知道他们要失去妻子或女朋友"
"The German soldier knows he's going to Iose his girl and his Iife."
(# men continue singing)
"每晚路灯都会点亮"
"The Iantern burns every night."
"我依然记得你的步伐."
"It knows your steps and the way you walk."
"每夜都在燃烧， 可我无时不在想念"
"It burns every night, but I've been Iong forgotten."
"我是否该受伤害,
"Should harm come to me,
谁同你一起
who will stand with you
在路灯之下的是,
under the Iantern with you,
莉莉·玛琳."
Lili Marleen."
(men) #Mit dir Lili Marleen
你在美国生活如何
What is your Iife Iike in America?
你有家庭吗? -是的，有个女儿
Do you have a family?  Yes, I have a daughter,
她有四个孩子.  四个?
and she has four children.  Four?
你一定以他们为骄傲了  是，我承认
You must be very proud of them.  Yes, I am. I admit it.
你妻子呢?  她几年前去世了
And where's your wife?  She died a few years ago.
Zigaretten?
你怎么样？有孩子么?  不
How about you? Do you have children?  No, I don't.
你在美国地位如何? 一定身居要职了
What is your position in America? It must be important.
不，其实也不是 只是联邦地方法院的法官
No, it isn't really. I'm a district court judge.
去年我就不做了.
I haven't even been that for the Iast year.
你退休了吗?  选举时退位了.
Are you retired?  Forcibly, by the electorate.
在美国法官是选举的吗?
You elect judges in the United States?
是的，有些州是这样的  我不知道
Yes, in some states.  I didn't know that.
这是司法体系的优点也是缺点.
It's either a virtue or a defect of our judiciary system.
我想去年我被淘汰也是好事.
I thought it was one of the virtues until Iast year, when I was defeated.
我想还是选举制度的问题， 不是你的错.
I'm sure it was the fault of the electorate, not yours.
There seems to be some difference of opinion about that.
我就住这.  这里?
This is where I Iive.  Here?
是的，里面还不错.
Yes. It's not so bad inside.
要上来喝杯咖啡么？.
Would you Iike to come up? I could make some coffee.
好的，谢谢
Yes, thank you.
生活不容易吧?
Things haven't been very easy for you, have they?
我不习惯太舒适.
I'm not used to them being easy.
我可没那么脆弱
I'm not fragile, Judge Haywood.
我是军人的女儿
I'm a daughter of the military.
你知道这意味着什么?  不，我不知道
You know what that means, don't you?  No, I'm afraid I don't.
这说明我是受纪律教育的
It means I was taught discipline.
一种很特别的纪律
A very special kind of discipline.
比如，在小时候 夏天我们要走很远到乡村.
For instance, as a child we would go for Iong rides into the country in the summer.
但是我从来不允许在路上像其他孩子一样喝柠檬水.
But I was never allowed to run to the Iemonade stand with the others.
我被教育要："控制干渴."
I was told "Control your thirst."
"控制饥饿."
"Control hunger."
"控制感情."
"Control emotion."
这对我帮助很大
It has served me well.
那你的丈夫呢？ 他也如此吗?
And your husband? Was he of that heritage, too?
我的丈夫是军人， 他只知道一件事-
My husband was a soldier. He was brought up to do one thing -
战斗，打好战
to fight in the battle and fight well.
咖啡还好吗?  很好，谢谢
Is the coffee all right?  Fine, thank you.
我加了伊砂特, 加重味道的.
It's ersatz, but I always try to make it strong.
很好
It's fine.
我很好奇
I'm curious.
你是怎么看欧内斯特·姜宁的?
What do you think of Ernst Janning?
柏斯德夫人， 我不好在庭外私自评论的.
Mrs Bertholt, I'm not at Iiberty to discuss the case outside of the courtroom.
噢，当然
Oh, yes. Of course.
我对他的事情知道一点 我们一同参加过音乐会.
I knew Ernst Janning a Iittle. We used to attend the same concerts.
There was a reception given for Wagner's daughter-in-Iaw.
当时西特勒也在
Hitler was there.
欧内斯特·姜宁和他妻子一起
Ernst Janning was there with his wife.
她很漂亮
She was very beautiful.
小巧可爱
Very small, very delicate.
她现在死了
She's dead now.
西特勒为她着迷了.
Hitler was quite taken with her.
他在接待会上接见她.
He made advances towards her during the reception.
他总是感情冲动.
He used to do things Iike that in a burst of emotion.
我不会忘记欧内斯特·姜宁制止他的一幕.
I will never forget the way Ernst Janning cut him down.
我想没有人那么对待过他.
I don't think anybody did it to him quite that way.
他说 "长官, 我对你的失礼并不在意."
He said "Chancellor, I do not object so much that you are so ill-mannered."
"我不介意你的失礼."
"I do not object to that so much."
"我只介意你竟是如此平庸."
"I object that you are such a bourgeois."
西特勒都气白了脸, 生气的离开了
Hitler whitened, stared at Janning and walked out.
咖啡还好吗?
Is the coffee really all right?
很好，谢谢
Fine, thank you.
像姜宁、我丈夫还有我这样的人们， 都憎恨西特勒.
Men Iike Janning, my husband and I, we hated Hitler.
我想要你知道 他恨我们.
I want you to know that. And he hated us.
他恨我的丈夫， 因为他是真的英雄,
He hated my husband because he was a real war hero,
然后他不能容忍.
and the Iittle corporal couldn't tolerate that.
他（西特勒）恨他娶到了贵族的女儿.
And he hated him because he married into nobility, which was my family.
西特勒害怕高贵， 但他憎恨.
Hitler was in awe of the nobility, but he hated it.
这就是所发生的， 很有讽刺意义.
That's why it's so ironic, what happened.
你知道我丈夫怎么样了?
You know what happened to my husband?
是
Yes.
他们指控他的罪名?
What did he know of the crimes they cited him for?
他同其他的战犯一起被审判
He was placed on trial with the other military Ieaders.
他是战争的牺牲品.
He was part of the revenge the victors always take on the vanquished.
这是政治谋杀.
It was political murder.
你可以明白的，不是吗?
You can see that, can't you?
柏斯德夫人, 我不明白.
Mrs Bertholt, I don't know what I see.
我或许真的不该同你谈这个.
I probably shouldn't be here talking with you about this at all.
我明白， 我真的想明白.
I want to understand. I do want to understand.
我不得不
I have to.
你还要咖啡吗?
Would you Iike some more coffee?
好的，谢谢
Yes, thank you.
Hi.  Hi.
我们找到爱琳·霍夫曼了.
We found Irene Hoffman.
哪里?  柏林.
Where?  Berlin.
柏林?
Berlin, eh?
她结婚了，她现在是叫沃尔纳 所以我们找不到她
She got married. Her name is Wallner now. That's why we couldn't Iocate her.
她什么时候来?  她不来
When is she coming?  She's not coming.
你说她不来是什么意思?  她不想来
What do you mean, she's not coming?  She doesn't want to come.
你也知道的， 没有人想再作证了.
You know what it's Iike. None of them want to testify any more.
如果午夜赶去， 明天下午我能赶回来.
If I catch the midnight, I can get to Berlin and be back by tomorrow afternoon.
你还没睡过...  如果找到霍夫曼那是值得的.
Tad, you haven't slept...  It will be worth it if I can get Hoffman.
明天早上法庭由你负责?
Take over for me in court in the morning, will you?
上校，你一来我就告诉过你.
(man) Colonel, please. I have told you this before when you first came in.
我现在再说一遍： 我们已经与此案无关了
I say it again now: we are through with all this.
她没必要去， 你没权力要她去
She does not have to go. You have no right to order her to.
沃尔纳先生, 我不是要命令她走. 我没有那样的权力.
Mr Wallner, lm not ordering her to go. I have no authority to do that.
你不是觉得我们出席审判就能获奖吧?
Do you think we get a medal for appearing at these trials?
人民不喜欢这样, 他们不喜欢德国人做出对同胞的不利证明.
The people do not like them, they do not want Germans to testify against Germans.
这两年我在不知情的情况下， 一直没有处理这些案子.
I haven't been prosecuting these cases for the past two years without knowing that.
你说走是很容易的.
It is easy for you to say go.
审判结束后你就回美国了， 但我们还是要同人民继续一起生活.
After the trials you go back to America, but we must live with these people.
沃尔纳先生, 你不觉得我知道我正要问的吗?
Mr Wallner, don't you think I realise what I'm asking?
你怎么可以像盖世太保一样...
How can you come in like the Gestapo...
因为他们要为自己的作为付出代价!
Because they must not be allowed to get away with what they did!
你认为他们到最后也不会逃脱吗?
Do you really think they won't get away with it in the end?
对天发誓如此.
I say the hell with them and the hell with you.
好
Hugo.
爱米尔·哈恩会在场吗?
Emil Hahn will be there?
是的，在法庭
Yes. In the dock.
欧内斯特·姜宁?
Ernst Janning?
是的.
Yes.
你看到楼下的店铺了吧.
You saw the store downstairs.
虽然小本经营， 但对我们来说是新的开始.
It's not much, but it's a new start for us.
如果我去纽伦堡他们就会来.
They will come if I go to Nuremberg.
他们会砸了店铺.
They will come and break the windows of the store.
我会让守卫24小时守护.
I'll place a guard in front of the store 24 hours a day.
你没必要去, 爱琳...  爱琳, 你务必要去.
You do not have to go, lrene...  lrene, you do have to go.
你要为那些站不起来的人民而去.
You have to go for all the people who can't get on the stand themselves.
你不亏欠任何人, 爱琳.  不，你有!
You do not owe it to anybody, lrene.  Yes, you do!
你至少对不起一个人.
You owe it to one person at least.
(sobs)
在晚上...
In the night...
每天晚上...
every night...
我们早知道会有这样的结果.
we've known somehow it would come to this.
Dr Geuter, 你还记得那标题吗?
(Radnitz) Dr Geuter, do you recognise that headline?
是的
Yes, sir.
你可以当庭宣读吗?
Would you read it to the tribunal?
"种族污染."
"Death to the race defiler."
在什么报纸里刊登的呢?  朱利叶斯日报.
In what newspaper did it appear?  Julius Streicher's Der Sturmer.
这同什么案子有关?
What was it in connection with?
费尔德斯特的案子.
The Feldenstein case.
什么费尔德斯特案子?
What was the Feldenstein case?
法官大人! 被告提交介绍费尔德斯特案子的资料.
Your Honour! The defence objects to introduction of the Feldenstein case.
这是个荒谬的案子, 只怕是当时期最荒谬的.
It is a notorious case, perhaps the most notorious of the period.
既没有相关主题， 又掺加感情因素.
It has overtones and appeals to emotion that would perhaps be best not raised.
与案件无关的资料不需提交.
There are no issues or overtones that may not be raised in this courtroom.
但本庭对案件相关的内容都感兴趣 反对驳回.
The tribunal is interested in everything that is relevant. Objection is overruled.
好，接下来我来.
It's all right. I'll take it.
-法官大人，可以继续吗? -请继续.
May it please the tribunal?  You may continue.
谢谢
Thank you.
那么， 费尔德斯特的案子到底是怎么回事呢?
Now, what was the Feldenstein case?
是有关原告因种族污染而指控被告.
The case of a man accused of racial pollution.
你能否解释一下什么是“种族污染”?
Will you explain what is meant by "racial pollution"?
这是根据纽伦堡法律来说的.
This is the charge that is referred to in the Nuremberg laws.
任何非印欧语系的人同印欧语系人种 发生性关系将有可能被判处死刑
Any non-Aryan having sexual relations with an Aryan may be punished by death.
你什么时候知道费尔德斯特的案子呢?
When did you first become acquainted with the Feldenstein case?
在1935年9月 警方联系到我.
In September 1 935 I was contacted by the police.
告诉我费尔德斯特先生被拘禁了
They said that Mr Feldenstein was being held
费尔德斯特先生要求我来做法律顾问
and that he requested that I serve as his counsellor.
他当时是什么出身?
What position did he hold in the community?
他是非常有名的商人.
He was a very well-known merchant.
他是纽伦堡犹太教会组织领导之一.
He was one of the heads of the Jewish Congregation in Nuremberg.
警方以什么罪名起诉他?
What was the nature of the charge against him?
他被起诉同16岁的爱琳·霍夫曼
He was accused of having intimate relations
有亲密关系
with a 16-year-old girl, lrene Hoffman.
我明白了
(Lawson) I see.
然后他对你说了什么?
And what did he say to you about the case?
他说是冤枉的.
He said it was false.
他说他早就认识小女孩同她的家人.
He said he knew the girl and her family a long time.
在父母死后他总去看她.
He'd gone to visit her since they died.
但是他们没有什么亲密关系.
But there had never been anything of the kind charged between them.
医生，能否请你告诉法庭接下来发生了什么?
Doctor, would you please tell the tribunal what happened then?
他在没有经过特别法庭审理就直接被起诉了.
He was indicted before the special court at Nuremberg.
特别法庭在哪里?
(Lawson) Where was this special court?
就在这里， 这里的特别庭.
It was right here. This building. This very courtroom.
盖特博士, 当时的审判庭情形如何?
Dr Geuter, what were the circumstances surrounding the trial?
是纳粹主义耀武扬威的地方.
It was used as a showplace for National Socialism.
当时正值纽伦堡9月欢庆.
It was the time of the September celebrations, the Nuremberg rallies.
法庭里人潮拥挤.
The courtroom was crowded.
就在后面站满了人.
Back there, people were standing up.
朱利叶斯就坐在前排的位置.
Julius Streicher was sitting in one of the front seats.
纳粹党的高员们也都到场了.
And high officials of the Nazi party were all over.
医生，能否告诉我们
Doctor, would you please tell us
你当时如何预料审判趋势?
what were your expectations for the trial in this climate?
我做最坏打算
I expected the worst
当我看到爱米尔·哈恩是公诉人
when I saw that Emil Hahn was the public prosecutor.
他是狂热分子
He was a fanatic.
他的审判以野蛮残酷著称
His trials were always marked by extreme brutality.
但我还是抱着一丝希望,
But I had one hope for the outcome,
因为坐在审判席的还有欧内斯特·姜宁.
because sitting on the judge's bench was Ernst Janning.
他的声誉全国知晓.
His reputation was known throughout Germany.
他以全身心贡献于法律正义闻名
He was known to have dedicated his life to justice, to the concept of justice.
谢谢，问答毕
Thank you. That's all.
还有问题吗?
(Haywood) Any questions?
谢谢，没有
Thank you. No questions.
请证人离席.
(Haywood) The witness is excused.
请求传召证人 爱琳·霍夫曼·沃尔纳出庭做证.
The prosecution calls to the stand lrene Hoffman Wallner.
请举右手?
Will you raise your right hand?
我向全能无所不知的主发誓
I swear by God the Almighty and Omniscient
我会说出事实的真相， 绝无虚假.
that I will speak the pure truth and withhold and add nothing.
我会的
I do.
可以告诉法庭你的名字吗?
Will you please state your name to the tribunal?
Irene Hoffman Wallner.
沃尔纳夫人, 你认识雷曼·费尔德斯特么?
Mrs Wallner, did you know Lehman Feldenstein?
是的
Yes.
你什么时候第一次遇到他?
When did you first meet him?
1925或1926年， 不是很确切.
It was 1 925 or 1 926. I am not sure exactly.
他当时几岁?  50多.
How old was he at this time?  He was in his fifties.
他被捕时又几岁?
And how old was he at the time of his arrest?
65. -我知道了.
He was 65.  I see.
你们两人是什么关系?
What was the nature of your relationship?
我们是朋友.
We were friends.
你父母死后你还见他吗?
Did you continue to see him after your parents died?
是.  为什么?
Yes.  Why?
我们是朋友 我住的房子也是他的
We were friends. He owned the building that I lived in.
他也要常在那一带做生意.
His business took him there quite often.
当警方讯问
Now, what did you say to the police
他同你的亲密关系时 你是怎么说的
when they questioned you about having intimate relations with him?
我说那都是胡说
I told them it was a lie.
可以告诉我当时的公诉人是谁吗?
Could you tell me who the public prosecutor was?
爱米尔·哈恩
Emil Hahn.
-爱米尔·哈恩讯问你了吗?  是.
Did Emil Hahn question you?  Yes.
他同你说了什么?
What did he say to you?
他把我带到另一个房间
He... took me into a separate room
只有我们两人
where we were alone.
他告诉我重复故事是没有用的
He told me that it was no use to repeat my story
因为没人会相信我
because no one would believe me.
因为有了种族污染,
That there had been race defilement,
唯一可以解救的就是杀死越轨者.
and the only pardon for this was to kill the violator.
他告诉我如果我偏袒费尔德斯特先生,
He told me that if I protected Mr Feldenstein,
我会以伪证罪被拘禁.
that I would be held under arrest for perjury.
你怎么答复他呢?
What did you reply to him?
我一遍又一遍的重复我说过的
I told him what I had said, again and again.
我告诉他我别无可说的了,
I told him that I could not say anything else,
我不能撒谎对不起我的恩人.
I could not lie about someone who had been so kind to me.
你被拘捕了吗?
Were you held under arrest?
是.
Yes.
沃尔纳夫人, 告诉我们,
Mrs Wallner, tell us,
爱米尔·哈恩在零讯时是什么态度?
what was the manner in which Emil Hahn conducted the prosecution?
他嘲笑
He made a mockery
费尔德斯特的一切辩解
of everything Mr Feldenstein tried to say in his own defence.
一有机会就奚落他.
He held him up to ridicule whenever possible.
听众们什么反映?
What was the reaction of the audience?
他们一次次的大笑.
They laughed again and again.
审判时间有多久?
How long did the trial last?
沃尔纳夫人?
Mrs Wallner?
审判维持了多久?
How long did the trial last?
两天
Two days.
第二天陪审团的裁决通过了吗?
Was the verdict passed at the end of the second day?
是.
Yes.
裁决如何?  有罪.
What was the verdict?  Guilty.
判决如何?
And what was the sentence?
费尔德斯特被处死刑
Mr Feldenstein was sentenced to be executed.
我以伪证判处两年监禁.
I was sentenced to be in prison for two years for perjury.
当时谁是首席法官?
Who was the presiding judge?
欧内斯特·姜宁
Ernst Janning.
判决生效了吗?
Were the sentences carried out?
非常感谢 我没有问题了
Thank you very much, Mrs Wallner. That's all.
还有问题吗?
Any questions?
法官大人, 我请求保留证人
Your Honour, I would like to request that the witness be kept available.
一旦时机合适，
We will present further evidence on the Feldenstein matter
在费尔德斯特一案中 我们会提供进一步的证据
when it comes time for the defence to present its case.
证人请做好再次出庭准备.
The witness will please hold herself so available.
现在你可以离庭了
You may go. You're excused now.
(Haywood) Colonel Lawson.
法官大人， 我要求出示由西特勒颁布的法令
Your Honours, I offer in evidence a decree, signed by Adolf Hitler,
任何人因为不忠或抵抗，
directing that all persons accused or suspected of disloyalty or resistance of any sort
可以进行秘密逮捕拘留
might be arrested secretly,
可以秘密进行，不经审判,
with no notice to friends or relatives, without any trial whatsoever,
拘禁在集中营.
and put into concentration camps.
我还可以提供一组在此法令下做出的决定书,
I also offer a group of orders issued under that decree,
都是由被告们签署,
each one signed by one of the defendants,
以至数以千计的人被捕
by which hundreds of persons were arrested
关押到了集中营
and placed in concentration camps.
签署人有：弗里德·霍夫斯特
Signed by Friedrich Hofstetter,
沃纳·兰谱,
Werner Lampe,
爱米尔·哈恩,
Emil Hahn,
欧内斯特·姜宁.
Ernst Janning.
法官大人， 今天在席的被告
Your Honours, the defendants on trial here today
本身没有管理集中营.
did not personally administer the concentration camps.
他们从来没有鞭打受害者,
They never had to beat victims,
或者给他们灌毒气.
or pull the lever that released gas into the chambers.
但是根据我们提供的证据显示,
But as the documents we have introduced into this case have shown,
被告们都是法律的实施者,
these defendants fashioned and executed laws,
他们做出了裁决
and rendered judgments
以至百万人被判决.
which sent millions of victims to their destinations.
兰迪兹少校.
Major Radnitz.
法官大人，我请求劳森上校做证
Your Honours, I would like to request that Colonel Lawson be sworn in as a witness.
-准许.  谢谢.
Granted.  Thank you.
请举右手?
Will you raise your right hand?
我向全能无所不知的主发誓
I swear by God the Almighty and Omniscient
我会说出事实的真相， 绝无虚假.
that I will speak the pure truth and withhold and add nothing.
我会的
I do.
1945年结束战争时你是否服役美国军队?
Were you active in the United States army in 1 945 at the close of the war?
是的
Yes, I was.
是否由你指挥部队解放集中营?
Were you in command of troops liberating concentration camps?
是的
I was.
你是否在达靠和贝尔森?  是
Were you in Dachau and Belsen?  Yes.
你是否需要向我们提供录象资料?
Were you present when the films we are about to see were taken?
是的
Yes, I was.
好
OK.
地图显示了集中营的方位
The map shows the number of and location of concentration camps under the Third Reich.
布痕瓦尔德集中营创建于1933年
Buchenwald concentration camp was founded in 1 933.
囚禁了80,000多人.
Its inmates numbered about 80,000.
在布痕瓦尔德有种说法:
There was a motto at Buchenwald:
"摧残肢体,
"Break the body,
折磨意志,
break the spirit,
销毁心脏."
break the heart."
都在布痕瓦尔德烤炉,
The ovens at Buchenwald,
处理尸体的证据.
evidence of last-minute efforts to dispose of bodies.
烤炉是由知名产家生产
The stoves were manufactured by a well-known company
同时， 这样的烤炉也是出名的面包烤炉.
which also specialised in baking ovens.
公司的名字已经知道了
The name of the firm is clearly inscribed.
布痕瓦尔德集中营的成品展,
An exhibit of by-products of Buchenwald,
展示在当地人和盟军面前.
displayed for the local townspeople by an Allied officer.
Brushes of every description.
鞋子  大人们和小孩的
Shoes  adults' and children's.
眼镜
Spectacles.
牙齿上的金子，被融化了
Gold from teeth, melted down,
每月都会被送往沃尔封SS.
sent once a month to the medical department of the Waffen SS.
用人皮做的灯罩.
A lampshade made from human skin.
用来绘画的人皮,
Skin being used for paintings,
都是淫秽作品.
many having an obscene nature.
两个波兰劳工的头颅,
The heads of two Polish labourers,
缩小到只有原1/5大小.
shrunken to one-fifth their normal size.
骨盆架被用作烟灰缸.
A human pelvis used as an ashtray.
孩子们被纹身标志做最后的处决.
Children who had been tattooed to mark them for eventual extermination.
有时孩子们会被给予怜悯.
Sometimes mercy was shown to the children.
他们会被注射吗啡
They were injected with morphia
然后他们会在无知觉中被绞死.
so they'd be unconscious when hanged.
有一名医生描述如何执行绞刑,
One of the doctors described how they'd then place ropes around their necks,
用医生的语言描述就是:
and in the doctor's own words:
"就像图画一样， 他们被钓死在墙上."
"Like pictures, they were then hanged by hooks on the walls."
大批人员在集装车厢中运输,
The bodies of those who had come in boxcars,
没有足够的食物和空气,
without food and without air,
最后坚持不到达靠.
who hadn't survived the journey to Dachau.
数以千计的人被用作白老鼠，
Hundreds of inmates were used as human guinea pigs
用作医学实验对象
for atrocious medical experiments.
一位现场的目击证人给出如下描述:
A witness at an execution at Dachau gave the following description:
"他们被要求脱光衣服."
"lnmates were made to leave their clothing on a rack."
"他们以为是去洗澡."
"They were told they were going to take baths."
"然后门就锁上了."
"Then the doors were locked."
"大量的毒气从管道中喷出."
"Tins of Zyklon B were released through the specially constructed apertures."
"你可以听到里面的呻吟残叫声."
"You could hear the groaning and the whimpering inside."
"两三分钟后， 一切归于平静."
"After two or three minutes, all was quiet."
死亡数据统计 90,000 来自斯洛伐克
Death transports that had arrived included 90,000 from Slovakia,
65,000 来自希腊
65,000 from Greece,
11,000 来自法国
1 1,000 from France,
90,000 来自荷兰
90,000 from Holland,
400,000 来自匈牙利
400,000 from Hungary,
250,000 来自波兰和中欧地区
250,000 from Poland and Upper Silesia,
另外100,000 来自德国
and 100,000 from Germany.
这些就是当盟军解放贝尔森集中营的时候
And this is what was filmed
所拍摄到的
when British troops liberated Belsen concentration camp.
处于卫生考虑， 只好用推土机尽快掩埋尸体
For sanitary reasons a British bulldozer had to bury the bodies as quickly as possible.
这些尸体是谁?
Who were the bodies?
欧洲被占领国家的人民.
Members of every occupied country of Europe.
欧洲2/3的犹太人遭到了灭绝.
Two-thirds of the Jews of Europe... exterminated.
超过了6，000，000
More than six million,
这是根据纳粹的数据报告.
according to reports from the Nazis' own figures.
但真实的数据又是多少呢...
But the real figure...
没有人知道
no one knows.
他们怎么敢让我们看那些录象? 怎么敢?
How dare they show us those films? How dare they?
我们不是刽子手! 我们是裁判者.
We are not executioners! We are judges.
你认为不该是那样的对吗?
You do not think it was like that, do you?
那是执行死刑， 不过不应该是那样的.
There were executions, yes, but nothing like that.
根本不该是!
Nothing at all!
波!
Pohl!
是你同艾克曼负责集中营的,
You ran those concentration camps, you and Eichmann.
他们说我们屠杀了百万人
They say we killed millions of people.
百万人!
Millions of people!
怎么可能?
How could it be possible?
告诉他们！ 怎么可能?
Tell them! How could it be possible?
是可以的
It's possible.
如何做?
How?
你说技术上?
You mean technically?
全要依靠你的工具设备.
It all depends on your facilities.
你有两幢每单间可以容纳2，000人的房间.
Say you have two chambers that accommodate 2,000 people apiece.
总的算一下
Figure it out.
在半小时内就可以解决10，000人
It's possible to get rid of 1 0,000 in a half hour.
你也不需要让守卫来动手
You don't even need guards to do it.
你告诉他们要洗澡了,
You can tell them they are going to take a shower,
接下来你不是开水龙头， 只要开毒气就可以了.
and then instead of the water, you turn on the gas.
杀人不是问题， 问题是如何处理尸体.
It's not the killing that is the problem. It's disposing of the bodies.
那才是问题
That's the problem.
# Das ist schon
# Wunderschon
# Das tut gut
# Was man alles im Liebesrausch tut
# Und zur Nacht flliegt ein fllusterndes Fleh'n
# "ach verweile, du bist ja so schon"
# Doch die Liebe bleibt nur, wo sie ist
# Wenn man immer aufls neue sich kusst
# Und so lebt...
对不起，我迟到了.  没关系.
I'm sorry I'm late.  That's all right.
我在处理重建委员会的事情.
I was doing some work for the rebuilding committee.
我给你带了文件看看， 好决定接下来要怎么办.
I brought you some folders so we can decide what you should see next.
那才是真正的房屋艺术.
There's the Albrecht Durer house. And the museum.
你认为你什么时候可以处理?  随时.
When do you think you could make it?  Any time.
现在可以点菜了吗?  让我来点好吗?
Would you like to order now?  Can I help you with the menu?
我想我什么都不要，谢谢.
I don't think I'll have anything, thank you.
一杯摩泽尔葡萄酒
A glass of Moselle, please.
摩泽尔
Moselle.
怎么了?
What is the matter?
没什么，我就是不饿
Nothing. I'm just not hungry, that's all.
你知道...
You know...
最后的日子对我很重要.
the last few days have meant a great deal to me.
怎么?
How?
我想你不知道我曾四处流浪.
I don't think you realise what a provincial man I really am.
在这之前我也出国过一次.
I've been abroad just exactly once before this.
那时是“一战”时， 我是一名步兵.
That was when I was a doughboy in World War l.
以前我总到这些地方， 很好奇.
I used to pass places like this and wonder what they were like.
他们对我也影响很大  怎么?
They've meant a great deal to me, too.  How?
他们给了我美国一样的感觉.
They gave me back the feeling I had of the Americans.
当我在你的国家时所有的那种感觉.
The feeling I used to have when I was in your country.
真遗憾这不是什么杂志故事
It's too bad this isn't a magazine story.
为什么?
Why?
如果是，我们两个 一个成熟老迈的法学家...
If it were, two people like us, the rapidly ageing jurist...
噢，不
Oh, no.
一个成熟老迈的法学家和一个漂亮的寡妇
The rapidly ageing jurist and the beautiful widow
将会克服重重困难， 穿越各种险阻.
would transcend their difficulties and travel places either by land or by sea.
今天我见到马克斯
I saw Mr Perkins today.
他告诉我在法庭展示的录象
He told me they showed those pictures in the courtroom,
劳森上校最喜欢的图片
Colonel Lawson's favourite pictures.
他总是推脱不肯出示，对吧?
He drags them out at any pretext, doesn't he?
劳森上校的个人恐怖收藏
Colonel Lawson's private chamber of horrors.
这就是你认为的我们? 你认为我们知道这些事情吗?
Is that what you think we are? Do you think we knew of those things?
你觉得我们希望屠杀妇女和小孩么?
Do you think we wanted to murder women and children?
你相信吗? 信么?
Do you believe that? Do you?
柏斯德夫人, 我不知道要相信什么
Mrs Bertholt, I don't know what to believe.
天， 我们在这里喝酒
Good God. We're sitting here drinking.
你怎么就认为我们知道?
How could you think that we knew?
我们不知道
We did not know.
We did not know!
据我所知， 这个国家的人都不知道.
As far as I can make out, no one in this country knew.
柏斯德夫人,你丈夫是军队指挥之一.
Mrs Bertholt, your husband was one of the heads of the army.
那么我来告诉你， 他不知道.
And he did not know. I tell you, he did not know.
是西姆莱、戈贝斯和SS， 他们知道发生了什么事情
It was Himmler. It was Goebbels. The SS knew what happened.
我们不知道
We did not know.
听着，事情有两面性.
Listen to me. There are things that happened on both sides.
我丈夫一生都是军人.
My husband was a military man all his life.
他应该享受军人的葬礼， 这也是他希望的.
He was entitled to a soldier's death. He asked for that.
我只是想为他争取， 仅仅如此而已.
I tried to get that for him. Just that, that he would die with some honour.
我四处拜访!
I went from official to official. I begged for that!
他应该死的尊严.
That he should be permitted the dignity of a firing squad.
你知道发生什么了吗.
You know what happened.
他同其他人一样被绞死了， 我恨所有人.
He was hanged with the others. And after that, I knew what it was to hate.
我没有离开房间一步， 只是酗酒
I never left the house. I never left the room. I drank.
我恨一切， 恨我所认识的一切美国人.
I hated with every fibre of my being. I hated every American I've ever known.
但我知道人不能因为仇恨活着.
But one can't live with hate. I know that.
丹,
Dan,
如果我们要继续生活， 就要学会遗忘.
we have to forget if we are to go on living.
(crowd singing "Liebeslied")
# Du darflst aufl mich bauen
# WeiBt ja, wie gut ich dir bin
# Ja, ja, ja, ja
# Weisst doch, wie gut ich dir bin.
# Und, und, wenn in der Ferne
# Dir, dir, mein Bild erscheint
# Dann, dann, wunscht' ich so gerne
# Dass uns die Liebe vereint
罗尔福.
Herr Rolfe.
尊敬的法官大人.
May it please the tribunal.
昨天看过了录象资料.
Yesterday the tribunal witnessed some films.
那些是……骇人听闻的录象.
They were... shocking films.
另人震惊的录象
Devastating films.
作为德国人,
As a German,
我为这样的事情发生在我国而羞耻.
I feel ashamed that such things could have taken place in my country.
这是毫无道理的,
There can never be a justification for them,
世世代代都不会有道理.
not in generations, not in centuries.
但是...
But...
我认为这也没错,
I do think it was wrong,
在此情此景，展示这些录象资料
indecent and terribly unfair of the prosecution
对于在席的被告，这是非常下流
to show such films in this case, in this court, at this time
无耻的公诉!
against these defendants!
我不得不强烈抗议这样的做法.
And I cannot protest too strongly against such tactics.
公诉人到底想要证明什么?
What is the prosecution trying to prove?
难道是全德国人都要对事件负责?
That the German people as a whole were responsible for these events?
或者还是全德国人都是知情的?
Or that they were even aware of them?
如果是的话,
Because, if he is,
那他就不是陈述事实
he's not stating facts
他知道他不是.
and he knows he's not.
军事操作的秘密,
The secrecy of the operations,
战俘营的地理方位,
the geographical location of the camps,
战争后期通信的破坏
the breakdown of communications in the last days of the war
当死亡变成了百万之数,
when the exterminations rose into the millions,
这只能说明他不是在说明事实.
show only too clearly that he is not telling the truth.
事实是这些暴行是由少数人操作的.
The truth is that these brutalities were brought about by the few extremists.
那些罪犯.
The criminals.
极少数德国人知道发生了什么.
Very few Germans knew what was going on.
极少
Very few.
我们到不知道录象中的地方， 发生了什么事情
None of us knew what was happening in the places shown on these films.
没有一个知道
None of us.
但最讽刺的是
But the most ironic part of it
检查官却以此公诉对抗被告,
is that the prosecution showed these films against these defendants,
被告只为一个理由而拥有权力:
men who stayed in power for one reason only:
防止更坏的结果发生
to prevent worse things from happening.
谁才是更勇敢的人呢?
Who is the braver man?
在危难中逃跑或辞职的人?
The man who escapes or resigns in times of peril?
还是置身死不顾坚守岗位的人?
Or the man who stays on his post at the risk of his own personal safety?
被告接下来出示的证人证物
The defence will present witnesses and letters and documents
来自全球各界宗教团体
from religious and political refugees all over the world
说明欧内斯特·姜宁是怎么样从死刑中解救了他们
telling how Ernst Janning saved them from execution.
被告还会证明
The defence will show the many times
在没有欧内斯特·姜宁法官作用影响下
Ernst Janning was able to effect mitigation of sentences,
结果会更严重
when without his influence the results would have been much worse.
被告还会证明
The defence will show
欧内斯特·姜宁的私人医生是非雅利安人
that Ernst Janning's personal physician was a non-Aryan.
保留一个犹太人出席作证是相当危险.
A Jewish man who he kept in attendance, much to his own peril.
被告方宣誓
The defence presents affidavits
from legal authorities and famed jurists the world over,
恳求在此案中要特别考虑,
pleading that special consideration must be made in this case,
欧内斯特·姜宁所有的工作灵感都源于:
saying that the entire work of Ernst Janning was inspired by one motive only:
尽力保存正义以及正义感.
the endeavour to preserve justice and the concept of justice.
现在，公诉人还有什么要对抗的呢?
Now, what has the prosecution to offer against this?
在针对欧内斯特·姜宁的起诉中，
The prosecution, in fact, has presented in the case of Ernst Janning
只有一件有事实根据的证据.
only one tangible piece of evidence.
费尔德斯特的案子 正如被告说的一样：臭名远播
The Feldenstein case. A notorious case, as the defence said.
一件不应开审的案子.
A case which never should have been reopened.
一件另被告不得不审理的案子.
A case which the defence is obliged to review now.
被告请求艾尔莎夫人出庭作证.
The defence calls Mrs Elsa Lindnow.
请举右手?
Will you raise your right hand?
我向全能无所不知的主发誓
I swear by God the Almighty and Omniscient
我会说出事实的真相， 绝无虚假.
that I will speak the pure truth and withhold and add nothing.
我会的
I do.
艾尔莎夫人
Mrs Lindnow.
你的工作是?
What is your occupation?
清洁女工.
I am a cleaning woman.
哪里工作?
Where are you employed?
格罗配街345号
4... 345 Grosseplatz.
你认识雷曼·费尔德斯特么? -是的，认识
Did you know Lehman Feldenstein?  Yes, I knew him.
怎么认识的?  在1935我给他干活.
In what capacity?  He was my employer in 1935.
你认识爱琳·霍夫曼么?
Do you know Mrs lrene Hoffman Wallner?
是
Yes.
怎么认识的?  她是那里的房客.
In what capacity?  She was a tenant in the building.
你有没有见到霍夫曼小姐同费尔德斯特先生一起?
Did you ever see Miss Hoffman and Mr Feldenstein together?
是.  到底怎么回事?
Yes.  How did this happen?
费尔德斯特先生到 霍夫曼小姐的公寓去看她
Mr Feldenstein came to see Miss Hoffman at her apartment.
经常吗?  常常
Often?  Quite often.
你有发现什么不正常的情况吗?
Were there any occasions in which you noticed anything unusual?
是
Yes.
我见到霍夫曼小姐在楼下， 吻了费尔德斯特先生
I saw Miss Hoffman kissing Mr Feldenstein at the door of her apartment.
还有其他场合吗?  是的，有一次.
Was there any other occasion?  Yes. There was one.
怎么样?  我到了霍夫曼小姐的房间.
What was it?  I came to Miss Hoffman's apartment.
我以为没人， 所以就去清理.
I wanted to clean up. I thought it was empty.
我看到霍夫曼小姐坐在费尔德斯特先生的大腿上.
I saw Miss Hoffman sitting on Mr Feldenstein's lap.
谢谢，就这些了
Thank you, Mrs Lindnow. That's all.
劳森上校?
Colonel Lawson?
请戴上耳机
Earphones, please.
夫人, 你的政治面貌?
Mrs Lindnow, what are your political affiliations?
政治面貌?
Political?
反对，法官大人.
Objection, Your Honour.
证人的政治面貌同她的证词无关.
This witness' political affiliations have nothing to do with the testimony.
劳森上校再次企图用感情因素影响审判
Colonel Lawson is again trying to appeal to the emotion of the court.
反对无效
Objection overruled.
请你回答?
Now would you answer the question, please?
你是纳粹党吗?
Were you a member of the National Socialist party?
是
Yes, I was.
我们是被迫的
We were forced to be.
"我们是被迫的."
"We were forced to be."
你什么时候成为纳粹党成员的?
When did you become a member of the Nazi party?
1933.
1 933.
所有德国人在1933年都加入纳粹党吗?
Were all German nationals forced to become Nazi party members in 1 933?
请回答!
Please answer me, Mrs Lindnow!
你是否被迫成为纳粹党?
Were you forced to become a member of the Nazi party?
问毕
That's all.
证人离席
Witness is excused.
被告方继续.
Defence may continue.
被告方传召 爱琳·霍夫曼·沃尔纳出庭
The defence calls lrene Hoffman Wallner to the stand.
沃尔纳夫人
(Haywood) Mrs Wallner,
你的誓言依然有效.
you are still under oath.
沃尔纳夫人,你是自愿作证的吗?
Mrs Wallner, did you come here voluntarily?
你是自愿作证的吗?
Did you report voluntarily to speak as a witness?
是
Yes.
公诉人要求你出庭不是事实?
Is it not true that the prosecution asked you to come here?
你出庭时很不情愿?
That it was very disagreeable for you to come here?
在这样的年代， 不情愿是很正常的事情.
It is always very disagreeable to live over those times.
那同我知道的相符,
That would be in agreement with the information I have,
你是不愿出庭的. 谢谢
that you did not want to come. Thank you, Mrs Wallner.
沃尔纳夫人
Mrs Wallner,
纽伦堡法案是在1935年9月15日颁布的
the Nuremberg laws were stated September 1 5th, 1 935.
-当时你在哪?  在纽伦堡.
Where were you at that time?  In Nuremberg.
你知道这些法案吗?
Did you know these laws?
同犹太人发生关系是违法的?
That a physical relationship with Jews was against the law?
是
Yes.
你知道在纽伦堡， 特别是纽伦堡,
Were you aware that in Nuremberg, and in Nuremberg in particular,
别说身体接触了， 就是同犹太人的一般接触也是被歧视的?
not only a physical relationship with Jews was disdained, but every social contact?
是
Yes.
你知道那样你可能有危险吗?
Were you aware that it might have some danger for you personally?
是，我知道
Yes, I was aware of it.
但你怎么可以因为这些抛弃多年的友谊呢...
But how can you discard a friendship from day to day because of some...
那是另外的问题了,  我没有问你那个问题.
That is another question, Mrs Wallner. I did not ask you that question.
你知道吗?  是，我知道.
Were you aware of it?  Yes, I was aware.
那你们还是继续见面吗?
Yet you still continued to see each other?
是
Yes.
事实证明费尔德斯特先生给你买了很多甜点.
It was brought out that Mr Feldenstein bought you candy and cigarettes.
是
Yes.
还记得他给你买花吗?
Remember that sometimes he bought you flowers?
是，他给我买了很多东西.
Yes, he bought me many things.
那是因为他是好人.
That was because he was kind.
他是我认识的最好的人
He was the kindest man I ever knew.
你认识证人,爱尔莎夫人么?
Do you know the witness, Mrs Elsa Lindnow?
是的，认识
Yes, I know her.
她是你公寓的清洁女工吗?  是.
Was she a cleaner at your apartment?  Yes.
费尔德斯特先生是否有到你的公寓看你?
Did Mr Feldenstein come to see you at your apartment?
是.  多少次?
Yes.  How many times?
我不记得.
I don't remember.
几次?  是
Several times?  Yes.
很多次?  很多次
Many times?  Many times.
你吻他了吗?  是，我吻了他
Did you kiss him?  Yes, I kissed him.
不止一次?
Was there more than one kiss?
是
Yes.
但不是你说的那样.
But it was not in the way you are trying to make it sound.
他对我来说就像父亲， 超过了父亲
He was like a father to me. He was more than a father.
超过了父亲?! 你有坐在他腿上吗?
More than a father?! Did you sit on his lap?
反对!
Objection! Counsel is persecuting the witness
辩护律师在获取证词中迫害证人
in the pretext of gaining testimony.
反对无效
Objection overruled.
被告又在最初的地方扮演闹剧.
The defence is re-enacting what was a travesty of justice in the first place.
劳森上校, 现在是法官席在审理， 不是公诉方.
Colonel Lawson, the tribunal makes the rulings in this case, not the prosecution.
你可以继续.  你坐在他腿上吗?
You may proceed.  Did you sit on his lap?
是的，但那没有什么不可见人的.
Yes. But there was nothing wrong or ugly about it.
你坐在他腿上吗?
Did you sit on his lap?
是，但是……
Yes. But...
你坐在他腿上! 你还做了什么?
You sat on his lap! What else did you do?
不是像你说的那样.
There was nothing that you are trying to say, nothing like that.
你还做了什么, 沃尔纳夫人?
What else did you do, Mrs Wallner?
你到底要干什么?
What are you trying to do?
你是不是要...
Are you trying to...
为什么你不让我说出真相?
Why do you not let me speak the truth?
那正是我们要的,  事实，事实!
That's what we want, Mrs Wallner, the truth. The truth!
你承认你继续同他见面.
You admitted that you continued to see him.
你承认他到你的公寓.
You admitted that he came to your apartment.
你承认你吻了他， 坐在他腿上.
You admitted you kissed him. You admitted you sat on his lap.
那你还做了些什么?
What else do you admit to? What else?
不是， 不是像你说的一样
Nothing! There was nothing like you're trying to make it sound.
还有什么呢?  什么都没有，没有
What else?  There was nothing! Nothing.
不要!
Stop it!
别说了!
(stamps fleet)  Stop it!
还有什么要说的呢？
What else do you admit to, Mrs Wallner?
罗尔福!
Herr Rolfe!
我们还要这么做吗?
Are we going to do this again?
法官大人，在这样的压力下， 被告情绪...
Your Honour, the defendant has been under such stress that he is not aware...
我知道，我知道
I am aware. I am aware.
法官大人，被告要求陈述.
Your Honour, the defendant wishes to make a statement.
我认为被告有权利...  遵守秩序
I believe the defence has a right to...  Order, order.
遵守秩序!
Order!  (bangs gavel)
被告是否要发言?
Does the defendant wish to make a statement?
是的，我要发言
I wish to make a statement, yes.
法官大人，被告有权请求...
Your Honour, the defence has the right to request...
被告有权现在发言.
The defendant has the right to make his statement now.
我要同我的当事人谈谈.  他有权现在发言!
I have to speak with my client.  He has the right to make it now!
(sobbing)
现在休庭，明早10：30继续
Tribunal is adjourned until 1 0.30 tomorrow morning.
你在干吗?
(Rolfle) What are you doing?
你以为你在干吗?
What do you think you're trying to do?
他们已经有格林, 富兰克... 都完了.
They've had Goring, Frank, Streicher... That's over.
你以为我作为被告辩护律师很光荣吗?
Do you think I have enjoyed being defence counsel during this trial?
在庭上我不得不猥琐
There were things I had to do in that courtroom that made me cringe.
我为什么要这么做?
Why did I do them?
因为我想为德国人保留一些东西.
Because I want to leave the German people something.
我想要为他们保留仅有的尊严.
I want to leave them a shred of dignity.
我想要停止这样的审判.
I want to call a halt to these proceedings.
如果我们允许他们 像处理你一样对待每个德国人,
If we allow them to discredit every German like you,
我们就永远没有主宰自己的权利!
we lose the right to rule ourselves forever!
我们要向前看，不是向后看
We have to look at the future. We can't look back now.
你想让美国人长驻在此吗?
Do you want the Americans to stay here forever?
广岛和长崎就是最好的例子.
I could show you a picture of Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
无数被烧毁的尸体.
Thousands and thousands of burnt bodies.
女人和孩子
Women and children.
这就是他们崇高的道德?
Is that their superior morality?
你以为他们会把我们带到哪里? 他们知道吗?
Where do you think they take us? Do they know?
你以为他们都知道我们的难处吗?
Do you think they have any concept of our problems?
我对你说什么好呢?
What can I say to you?
说什么才能让你明白呢?
What can I say to you to make you see?
你什么都不用说了
There is nothing you can say.
不用了
Nothing.
(radio) Nothing has happened to alleviate the crisis.
The crisis reached a head this afternoon
when all rail travel between western zones and Berlin was stopped.
The blockade by land is now complete.
(music starts)
接下来我们要怎么做，将军? 撤消?
What do you think we're going to do, General? Withdraw?
不能， 如果我们在压力下撤消,
We can't. If we withdraw under pressure,
我们在全世界的威望都要受到影响.
our prestige all over the world is threatened.
共产分子也会大量泳入.
The Communists will move in on every front.
这些审判如何呢，将军? 你感觉如何呢?
What about these trials, General? How do you feel about them now?
我们要对审判负责,
We're committed to the trials,
但现实一点的做法是我们要加快审判进度.
but I think it would be realistic to accelerate them as much as possible.
如果他们向我们进攻时我们采取什么措施，将军?
What would happen if they fired on one of our planes, General?
到时我们自然要面对， 现在没有答案.
We'll have to face that when it happens. There is no other answer to that now.
你应该尝尝这里的甜点， 很出名的.
You should try the strudel. It's excellent here.
不，谢谢
No, thanks.
丹, 我刚从柏林回来你知道的
Dan, I've just come back from Berlin, as you know.
我想本来不该是这样的， 我也不知道.
I don't think this is going to be it. A lot of people do, but I don't.
但可以肯定的是这是场斗争， 为将来的10年或20年.
But it is going to be a fight for survival  for the next ten years, maybe the next 20.
德国是能否幸存的关键.
Germany is the key to that survival.
高校学地理的同学就可以告诉你.
Any high-school student in geography can tell you that.
参议员，你到底想说什么?
Just what are you trying to say, Senator?
我要说的是:
What I'm trying to say is this:
没人想左右你的想法,
while nobody's trying to influence your decision,
意识到这个很重要 这是生活的真谛.
it's important that you realise this because it's a fact of life.
我们来面对吧，这是不详之兆啊.
Let's face it, gentlemen, the handwriting is on the wall.
我们要团结所有力量.
We're going to need all the help we can get.
我们需要德国人民的支持.
We're going to need the support of the German people.
还要甜点吗，先生们?
More strudel, gentlemen?
欧内·姜宁, 你可以开始了.
Herr Janning, you may proceed.
我想要证实一下费尔德斯特的案子
I wish to testify about the Feldenstein case
因为这是当时期最典型的案子.
because it was the most significant trial of the period.
法官席不仅要明白,
It is important not only for the tribunal to understand it,
对于全德国人民也是一样必要明白.
but for the whole German people.
为了可以理解它,
But in order to understand it,
必须要知道当时的时代背景.
one must understand the period in which it happened.
狂热恶疾覆盖了大地.
There was a fever over the land.
耻辱、污蔑、饥饿的恶疾.
A fever of disgrace, of indignity, of hunger.
我们有民主，是的,
We had a democracy, yes,
但已经在心底撕碎了.
but it was torn by elements within.
最重要的，还是恐惧.
Above all, there was fear.
害怕今天，明天
Fear of today, fear of tomorrow,
害怕我们的邻邦,
fear of our neighbours,
害怕我们自己.
and fear of ourselves.
只有当你理解
Only when you understand that
你才会明白西特勒对我们有多重要.
can you understand what Hitler meant to us.
因为他对我们说:
Because he said to us:
"抬起你的头， 以身为德国人而骄傲吧."
"Lift your heads. Be proud to be German."
"我们身边充斥了魔鬼  共产党, 自由主义者, 犹太人，吉普赛人."
"There are devils among us  communists, liberals, Jews, Gypsies."
"一旦魔鬼被消灭， 你们的烦恼也就解决了."
"Once these devils will be destroyed, your misery will be destroyed."
这是“牺牲品”的遥远传说.
It was the old, old story of the sacrificial lamb.
知道更多些的我们又怎么样呢?
What about those of us who knew better?
我们知道的只是谎言?
We who knew the words were lies and worse than lies?
我们为什么要沉默? 我们为什么要参加?
Why did we sit silent? Why did we take part?
因为我们爱我们的国家.
Because we loved our country.
极少数政治极端分子失势有什么区别?
What difference does it make if a few political extremists lose their rights?
少数民族失去权利又有何用?
What difference does it make if a few racial minorities lose their rights?
这都是必经阶段.
It is only a passing phase.
这是我们必须要走的路
It is only a stage we are going through.
不久这就将被抛弃
It will be discarded sooner or later.
西特勒不久也要被抛弃
Hitler himself will be discarded sooner or later.
"国家身处危险之中， 我们要大步走出阴影"
"The country is in danger! We will march out of the shadows."
"我们要前进" “前进”是很好的一个字眼
"We will go forward." "Forward" is the great password.
法官大人，历史也证实了
And history tells how well we succeeded, Your Honour.
我们成就了伟大的理想.
We succeeded beyond our wildest dreams.
西特勒鼓吹的权利和憎恨弥漫着德国,
The very elements of hate and power about Hitler that mesmerised Germany,
弥漫着全世界!
mesmerised the world!
我们发现竟然有如此强大的同盟.
We found ourselves with sudden powerful allies.
民主似乎在向我们招手.
Things that had been denied to us as a democracy were open to us now.
全世界都在说 "向前吧！拿去吧!"
The world said "Go ahead. Take it. Take it!"
"拿下苏台德区 拿下莱茵河."
"Take Sudetenland. Take the Rhineland. Remilitarise it."
"拿下整个奥地利."
"Take all of Austria! Take it."
然后有一天我们回头看看
And then one day we looked around
才发现我们更危险了.
and found that we were in an even more terrible danger.
仪式就在这法庭上展开,
The ritual began in this courtroom,
迅速蔓延全国!
swept over the land like a raging, roaring disease!
什么是必经之路
What was going to be a passing phase
已经成了生活的习惯
had become the way of life.
法官大人,
Your Honour,
我很满足可以静静地听审.
I was content to sit silent during this trial.
我很满足这样的看护.
I was content to tend my roses.
我很满足有辩护律师来拯救我的声誉...
I was even content to let counsel try to save my name...
until I realised that in order to save it
但我意识到死灰复燃.
he would have to raise the spectre again.
你们都已经见到了.
You have seen him do it.
他已经在庭上这么做了.
He has done it here in this courtroom.
他暗示第三帝国 为人民服务.
He has suggested that the Third Reich worked for the benefit of people.
他暗示西特勒统治下的德国为人民服务.
He has suggested that we sterilised men for the welfare of the country.
他暗示那个老犹太人是同16岁女孩发生了关系.
He suggested that perhaps the old Jew did sleep with the 1 6-year-old girl after all.
再次，这是为了国家利益.
Once more, it is being done for love of country.
要说出事实不容易
It is not easy to tell the truth.
但只要有拯救德国的办法
But if there is to be any salvation for Germany,
如果我们有罪就要承认,
we who know our guilt must admit it,
不管疼痛和羞辱.
whatever the pain and humiliation.
在我进入法庭之前，
I had reached my verdict on the Feldenstein case
在Feldenstein一案中我已经收到了陪审团的结果
before I ever came into the courtroom.
不管证据如何他都是有罪的， 这案子没有意义.
I would have found him guilty whatever the evidence. It was not a trial at all.
这是个“牺牲仪式”, 可怜的犹太人费尔德斯特是无辜的牺牲者.
It was a sacrificial ritual, and Feldenstein the Jew was the helpless victim.
法官大人， 被告不知道他在说什么.
Your Honour, the defendant is not aware of what he is saying.
他不知道其中的暗示.
He is not aware of the implications.
我知道，我知道!
I am aware. I am aware!
我的律师让你们相信
My counsel would have you believe
我们不知道集中营的事情.
we were not aware of the concentration camps.
不知道
Not aware.
我们当时在哪?
Where were we?
西特勒在国会宣泄愤怒时，我们在哪?
Where were we when Hitler began shrieking his hate in the Reichstag?
当我们的邻居们被抓去达靠，我们在哪?
When our neighbours were dragged out in the middle of the night to Dachau?
当每个村庄都有了铁路站台，我们在哪？
Where were we when every village in Germany has a railroad terminal
牛车上载满了孩子们时，
where cattle cars were filled with children being carried off to their extermination?
他们向我们哭叫，我们又在哪?
Where were we when they cried out in the night to us?
我们瞎了？哑了？聋了？
Were we deaf? Dumb? Blind?
法官大人，我要抗议
Your Honour, I must protest.
我的辩护律师辩护说， 我们不知道百万人灭绝的事情.
My counsel says we were not aware of the extermination of the millions.
还给你们找了借口
He would give you the excuse
我们似乎只知道数百人的灭绝.
we were only aware of the extermination of the hundreds.
这样就可以减轻罪孽吗?
Does that make us any the less guilty?
或许我们不知道细节,
Maybe we didn't know the details,
但如果我们不知道， 那也是因为我们不想知道
but if we didn't know, it was because we didn't want to know.
叛国者! 叛国者!  遵守秩序
Traitor! Traitor!  Order. Order.
遵守秩序!
Order!
把人带下， 到原来的位置.
Put that man back in his seat and keep him there.
我要告诉他们真相.
I am going to tell them the truth.
如果全世界都反对， 那我就说出真相.
I am going to tell them the truth if the whole world conspires against it.
我要告诉他们有关司法行政部的真相.
I am going to tell them the truth about their Ministry of Justice.
沃纳·兰谱, 现在在祈祷的人.
Werner Lampe, an old man who cries into his Bible now.
从每个被他送往集中营的人中
An old man who profited by the property expropriation
征收财产收益
of every man he sent to a concentration camp.
弗里德·霍夫斯特, 一个良好国民， 知道如何执行命令
Friedrich Hofstetter, the good German, who knew how to take orders,
把很多人送上了监狱.
who sent men before him to be sterilised, like so many digits.
爱米尔·哈恩,
Emil Hahn,
腐败、堕落的家伙
the decayed, corrupt bigot,
将自己的灵魂出卖给了魔鬼.
obsessed by the evil within himself.
还有欧内斯特·姜宁,
And Ernst Janning,
比他们都要坏...
worse than any of them...
因为他知道真相,
because he knew what they were,
但是还和他们狼狈为奸
and he went along with them.
欧内斯特·姜宁...
Ernst Janning, who made his life...
他的生活简直就是垃圾...
excrement...
因为他同他们一样同流合污.
because he walked with them.
法官大人,
Your Honour,
为欧内斯特·姜宁辩护是我的责任,
it is my duty to defend Ernst Janning,
虽然欧内斯特·姜宁 说他自己有罪.
and yet Ernst Janning has said he is guilty.
毫无疑问他有罪恶感.
There is no doubt he feels his guilt.
他在纳粹的行动中犯了错误,
He made a great error in going along with the Nazi movement,
但初衷却是为了国家利益.
hoping it would be good for his country.
但如果他被定有罪,
But, if he is to be found guilty,
还有其他追随者,
there are others who also went along,
也要被定有罪.
who also must be found guilty.
欧内斯特·姜宁说"我们成就了伟大的理想".
Ernst Janning said "We succeeded beyond our wildest dreams".
我们为什么会成功呢。法官大人?
Why did we succeed, Your Honour?
其他国家表现如何呢?
What about the rest of the world?
难道他们不知道第三帝国的决心?
Did it not know the intentions of the Third Reich?
他们没有听到西特勒的演说吗?
Did it not hear the words of Hitler broadcast all over the world?
难道他们不知道他对畿辅的意图吗,
Did it not read his intentions in Mein Kampfl,
全世界都发表了?
published in every corner of the world?
那么苏联的责任在哪,
Where is the responsibility of the Soviet Union,
在1939年签定和约， 发生了战争?
who signed in 1 939 the pact with Hitler that enabled him to make war?
现在要定俄国有罪吗?
Are we now to find Russia guilty?
1933年，同西特勒签定宗教协议的梵蒂冈
Where is the responsibility of the Vatican,
使得西特勒获得巨大声望
who signed in 1 933 the concordat with Hitler,
那它的责任又在哪?
giving him his first tremendous prestige?
难道我们现在说梵蒂冈有罪?
Are we now to find the Vatican guilty?
世界领袖之一， 丘吉尔的责任又在哪里,
Where is the responsibility of the world leader Winston Churchill,
在1938年伦敦时报发表的
who said in an open letter to the London Times in 1 938 -
1938, 法官大人
1 938, Your Honour -
"如果英国也遭受这样的灾难，
"Were England to suffer national disaster, I should pray to God
那就派遣阿道夫·西特勒来拯救吧."
to send a man of the strength of mind and will of an Adolf Hitler."
难道我们现在说丘吉尔有罪?
Are we now to find Winston Churchill guilty?
帮助西特勒制造武器的美国军火家们
Where is the responsibility of those American industrialists
从中收益
who helped Hitler to rebuild his armaments,
他们的责任又在哪里?
and profited by that rebuilding?
难道我们现在说美国的军火商有罪?
Are we now to find the American industrialists guilty?
不，法官大人
No, Your Honour. No.
不是单单德国有罪
Germany alone is not guilty.
全世界也像德国一样需要对西特勒负责.
The whole world is as responsible for Hitler as Germany.
审判处罚一个人很容易.
It is an easy thing to condemn one man in the dock.
可以简单说一些缺陷成就西特勒
It is easy to speak of the "basic flaw" in the German character
that allowed Hitler to rise to power,
同时又忽略了缺陷本身
and at the same time ignore the "basic flaw" of character
使得俄国签定协定， 丘吉尔称赞,
that made the Russians sign pacts with him, Winston Churchill praise him,
美国军火商收益!
American industrialists profit by him!
欧内斯特·姜宁说他有罪
Ernst Janning said he is guilty.
如果他是， 那么欧内斯特·姜宁的罪就是全世界的罪
If he is, Ernst Janning's guilt is the world's guilt.
不多不少如此
No more and no less.
将军， 我们要给予军事政府力所能及的帮助.
Major, we have to give the military governor every help we can give him.
每天要保证700吨的空中物资支援.
We have to get 700 tons in the air a day.
700吨
700 tons.
这是操作的问题.
This is some operation.
你有没有想过我们要支援煤和西红柿?
Did you ever think we'd be flying coal and tomatoes in these crates?
泰德, 我们已经是老朋友了
Tad, you and l have been friends a long time.
所以我叫你到这来
That's why I called you here.
明天在法庭你要怎么做?
What are you going to do in court tomorrow?
你很清楚我要怎么做吗
You know damn well what I'm going to do.
我知道你要把他们锁起来， 丢掉钥匙.
I know what you want to do  put them behind bars and throw away the key.
你知道这里发生了什么?
You know what's going on here now?
是，我知道
Yeah, I know what's going on.
你是军人， 你知道我们反对什么.
You're an army man. You know what we're up against.
其他人或许不知道， 但我要告诉你
The others may not, but you do. I'll tell you the truth.
我不知道如果他们向飞机攻击的话， 会发生什么事情.
I don't know what's going to happen if they fire on one of those planes.
我不知道会发生什么
I don't know what's going to happen.
但我知道: 如果通过柏林，就通过德国
But if I do know this: if Berlin goes, Germany goes.
通过德国，就通过欧洲
If Germany goes, Europe goes.
这就是原则.
That's the way things stand. That's the way they stand.
听着, Matt. 我的忍耐到极限了
Look, Matt. I'm going to go the limit.
我不是神...
And not you, not the Pentagon, not God on his throne is...
你以为你在跟谁说话?
Who do you think you're talking to?
你到底以为你在同谁说话?
Who the hell do you think you're talking to?
当你到达靠时我也在
When you were marching into Dachau, I was there too.
你以为我会忘记吗?
You think I'll ever forget it?
我不是你的指挥官， 也不会影响你的决定.
I'm not your commanding officer. I can't and won't influence your decision.
但我要告诉你, 直接让你明白.
But I want to give this to you, and I want to give it to you straight.
我们需要德国人民的支持.
We need the help of the German people.
把他们领导关押了并不能获得德国的帮助.
You don't get their help by sentencing their leaders to stiff prison sentences.
Tad, 现在要做的是如何幸存，不是吗?
Tad, the thing to do is survive, isn't it?
以最好的方式幸存不是吗.
Survive as best we can, but survive.
笑笑吧,
Just for laughs, Matt.
战争的意义到底是什么?
What was the war all about?
有什么意义?
What was it about?
这些都是针对被告的书面证据
That concludes presentation of documentary evidence against these defendants.
法官大人,
Your Honours,
战后三年的欧洲,
during the three years that have passed since the end of the war in Europe,
人类并没有获得太平.
mankind has not crossed over into Jordan.
在我们的国家， 战争的恐惧再次苏醒
In our own country, fear of war has been revived
我们要再次审视被告.
and we must look once more to our defences.
有冷战的说法， 女人和孩子死于非真正的战争,
There's talk of cold war while men and women die in real wars,
迫害和暴行不会真正消寂.
and the echoes of persecution and atrocities will not be stilled.
这些虽然没有帮助， 却还是值得留意.
These events cannot help but colour what happens in this courtroom.
但在这些事件中,
But somewhere in the midst of these events,
我们在庭上审理的犯罪事实
the responsibility for the crimes that we brought forward during this trial
必须从正确的角度来审视
must be placed in true perspective.
这是你现在要面临的问题， 法官大人
And this is the decision that faces Your Honours.
这是我们进退两难的时候.
It is the dilemma of our times.
It is a dilemma that rests with you.
公诉完毕.
The prosecution rests.
被告可以做最后陈词了.
The defendants may now make their final statements.
被告爱米尔·哈恩 可以陈词了.
Defendant Emil Hahn may address the tribunal.
法官大人, 我不会逃避我的责任
Your Honours, I do not evade the responsibility for my actions.
相反的，我会向全世界承认它们.
On the contrary, I stand by them before the entire world.
但我不会遵循别人的政策.
But I will not follow the policy of others.
我不会昨天说我们的政策对了
I will not say of our policy today that it was wrong
然后说我们今天的政策错了
when yesterday I say it was right.
德国在为生存而挣扎
Germany was fighting for its life.
出于自卫，某些政策是需要的.
Certain measures were needed to protect it from its enemies.
我不能说我这么做错了.
I cannot say that I am sorry we applied those measures.
我们是对抗布尔什维克的壁垒.
We were a bulwark against Bolshevism.
我们是西方文化的基石.
We were a pillar of Western culture.
壁垒和基石是西方都需要保存的.
A bulwark and a pillar the West may yet wish to retain.
被告弗里德·霍夫斯特 可以陈词了.
The defendant Friedrich Hofstetter may address the tribunal.
我终生都为国效忠,
I have served my country throughout my life,
不管我被分配到了哪里,
and in whatever position I was assigned to,
只是尽忠职守.
in faithfulness, with a pure heart and without malice.
我心中只有一个信念,
I followed the concept that I believed to be the highest in my profession,
信念就是:
the concept that says:
牺牲小我的正义， 服从法律,
to sacrifice one's own sense of justice to the authoritative legal order,
只遵守法律,
to ask only what the law is,
不要询问法律是否正义.
and not to ask whether or not it is also justice.
做为执法者，我只能如此.
As a judge, I could do no other.
我相信法官大人明白的，
I believe Your Honours will find me, and millions of Germans like me,
很多德国人像我一样,
who believed they were doing their duty to their country,
认为他们只是效忠，无罪
to be not guilty.
被告沃纳·兰谱 可以陈词了
The defendant Werner Lampe may address the tribunal.
法官大人...
Your Honours...
被告欧内斯特·姜宁 可以陈词了.
The defendant Ernst Janning may address the tribunal.
我没有什么好多说了.
I have nothing to add to what I have said.
证词收集完毕, 法庭辩论也结束了.
Testimony has been received, final arguments have been heard.
审判程序结束， 但是法官席需要时间考虑.
There remains nothing now but the task of the tribunal to render its decision.
法官席考虑到发布告示为止
The tribunal will recess until further notification.
我已经根据国内法和国际法
I've collected precedents and arguments
that have a bearing on the basis of the case,
引用收集和案件相关的争论的焦点
which is the conflict between allegiance to international law
and to the laws of one's own country.
丹, 我们有一大堆资料要看
Dan, we have a mountain of material to go over here.
你在看什么呢, 丹?  恩?
What are you looking at, Dan?  Mm?
我在看一些逮捕证的照片.
I was looking at some of these pictures attached to the warrants for arrest.
什么照片?
What pictures?
这是皮特斯.
There's Petersen before they operated on him.
这是爱琳·霍夫曼.
Here's lrene Hoffman.
当时她只有16岁不是吗?
She really was 1 6 once, wasn't she?
费尔德斯特
Feldenstein.
这个孩子，多少也不过14岁
And here's a boy  he certainly couldn't have been more than 1 4 -
被捕是因为说了不忠帝国的话.
executed for saying things against the Third Reich.
"根据弗里德·霍夫斯特法官命令执行."
"By order of Justice Friedrich Hofstetter."
对了，还有更多相关资料,
If I may say so, more pertinent to the legal basis of the case,
我有法国检举人给军事法庭的意见
I have the address of the French prosecutor
before the international military tribunal.
很显然，对于命令的直接执行者
"lt is obvious that, in the state organised along modern lines,
他们是有责任的
responsibility is confined to those who act directly for the state."
"尽管他们只是发布命令,
"Since they alone are in a position to judge the legitimacy of the given orders,
但一样会被检举."
they alone can be prosecuted."
我还有里斯教授的意见 -
I have another from Professor Jahreiss -
"法律角度: 主要战犯的审理".
"Legal aspects: trial of the major war criminals".
根据这些，
On the basis of these, I don't see where the prosecution
我真的不清楚检举人针对被告什么
has put forth a really clear-cut case against the defence
pertaining to the charges in the indictment.
考虑效忠以外的因素,
Regardless of the acts committed, we cannot make the interpretation
我们无法解释他们是否需要对行为负责.
that these defendants are really responsible for crimes against humanity.
你在想什么呢, 丹?  我们已经讨论了一整天了!
What do you think, Dan?  We've been going over this all day!
如果现在还不清楚...
If it isn't clear now...
难道你不来看看吗?
Aren't you going to look at these precedents?
你一点都不感兴趣吗?
Aren't you interested at all?
我很感兴趣. 你在说人性犯罪,
I'm interested, Curtiss. You were speaking of crimes against humanity,
被告们无须为他们的行为负责.
saying the defendants were not responsible for their acts.
我希望你可以解释给我听.
I'd like you to explain that to me.
我刚才就在解释.  也许.
I've just been explaining it.  Maybe.
但我听到的都是一些含糊的法律条规的说法.
But all I've heard is a lot of legalistic double talk and rationalisation.
你知道， 当我初次成为法官
You know, when I first became a judge
我知道我就要避免接触一些人.
I knew there were certain people in town I wasn't supposed to touch.
这是法官的中立性决定的.
I knew that if I was to remain a judge, this was so.
但你要我从另外一个角度怎么看
But how in God's name do you expect me to look the other way
谋杀6，000，000人?
at the murder of six million people?
我知道不是...  我不是让你换个角度.
I'm sure he didn't mean...  I'm not asking you to look the other way.
我是问你如何更好的顺应政策?
I'm asking you what good is it going to do to pursue this policy?
你说他们无罪.
Curtiss, you were saying that the men are not responsible for their acts.
你需要做出解释.
You're going to have to explain that to me.
而且要解释的很清楚.
You're going to have to explain it very carefully.
法官出席
The tribunal is now in session.
上帝保佑美国及检举人.
God bless the United States of America and this honourable tribunal.
在历经8个月的审判.
The trial conducted before this tribunal began over eight months ago.
有10,000 多页的证据记录,
The record of evidence is more than 1 0,000 pages long,
总结了辩护律师的最后陈述.
and final arguments of counsel have been concluded.
残酷的谋杀和暴行
Simple murders and atrocities
与本案无关
do not constitute the gravamen of the charges in this indictment.
正确的说
Rather, the charge is that of conscious participation
这样的罪行是全局的责任,
in a nationwide, government-organised system of cruelty and injustice,
in violation of every moral and legal principle known to all civilised nations.
法官席认真考虑过
The tribunal has carefully studied the record
参考了足够的证据
and found therein abundant evidence
对被告的起诉内容表示怀疑.
to support beyond a reasonable doubt the charges against these defendants.
(murmuring)
罗尔福, 在他有利的辩护中,
Herr Rolfe, in his very skilful defence,
宣称有其他
has asserted that there are others
需要承担责任的组织
who must share the ultimate responsibility
for what happened here in Germany.
这是事实
There is truth in this.
抱怨的政党在这里受到公开审判.
The real complaining party at the bar in this courtroom is civilisation.
但主谋负责人更要负责
But the tribunal does say that the men in the dock are responsible for their actions.
穿上法官袍的人
Men who sat in black robes,
审判着其他人.
in judgment on other men.
参与法律制定的人,
Men who took part in the enactment of laws and decrees,
目的却是要毁灭全人类.
the purpose of which was the extermination of human beings.
执法者
Men who, in executive positions,
更是参与行动，
actively participated in the enforcement of these laws,
违法的执行
illegal even under German law.
各国刑法共有这样的通则：
The principle of criminal law in every civilised society has this in common:
任何人唆使他人犯罪,
any person who sways another to commit murder,
任何人提供武器犯罪,
any person who furnishes the lethal weapon for the purpose of the crime,
任何人作为犯罪环节之一,
any person who is an accessory to the crime,
都归属有罪.
is guilty.
罗尔福另外指出
Herr Rolfe further asserts that the defendant Janning
姜宁是一名特殊的法官
was an extraordinary jurist
他做着效忠国家的事情
and acted in what he thought was the best interest of his country.
的确是事实
There is truth in this also.
姜宁, 是个悲剧人物
Janning, to be sure, is a tragic figure.
我们相信他憎恨邪恶
We believe he loathed the evil he did.
但是对他灵魂的怜悯
But compassion for the present torture of his soul must not beget forgetfulness
不能同他参与的罪行混淆
of the torture and the death of millions by the government of which he was part.
姜宁的一生在法庭上
Janning's record and his fate illuminate the most shattering truth
得到了回顾
that has emerged from this trial.
如果他及同其他被告因此被降级
If he, and all of the other defendants, had been degraded perverts,
或者第三帝国的领导者们都是恶魔,
if all of the leaders of the Third Reich had been sadistic monsters and maniacs,
那么自然就没有什么道德可言
then these events would have no more moral significance
than an earthquake, or any other natural catastrophe.
但审判中可以看出
But this trial has shown that under a national crisis
在那样的环境,
ordinary, even able and extraordinary men,
人人会犯罪也不奇怪
can delude themselves into the commission of crimes
想象一下
so vast and heinous that they beggar the imagination.
人们都不会忘记
No one who has sat through the trial can ever forget them.
人的扭曲仅因为政治
Men sterilised because of political belief.
背叛友谊和忠诚.
A mockery made of friendship and faith.
谋杀孩子
The murder of children.
都可以轻易的发生
How easily it can happen.
在我们的国家也都有
There are those in our own country too
尽管说着维护国家利益.
who today speak of the protection of country, of survival.
一切都是如此.
A decision must be made in the life of every nation.
在拼死相搏时,
At the very moment when the grasp of the enemy is at its throat,
最好的方法就是借刀杀人,
then it seems that the only way to survive is to use the means of the enemy,
to rest survival upon what is expedient,
to look the other way.
Well, the answer to that is... survival as what?
但国家不是岩石
A country isn't a rock.
国家不是个人的
It's not an extension of one's self.
它有它自己的利益
It's what it stands for.
国家在困难时更难维持.
It's what it stands for when standing for something is the most difficult.
面对全世界人民
Before the people of the world,
让我们坚守我们的誓言:
Iet it now be noted that here, in our decision, this is what we stand for:
正义、真相...
justice, truth...
还有人权的价值.
and the value of a single human being.
法庭对被告哈恩做出判决
The marshal will produce before the tribunal the defendant Hahn.
爱米尔·哈恩,
Emil Hahn,
本席判你有罪，终身监禁.
the tribunal finds you guilty and sentences you to life imprisonment.
今天你判决我， 明天布尔什维克就判决你!
Today you sentence me. Tomorrow the Bolsheviks sentence you!
法庭对被告霍夫斯特做出判决
The marshal will produce the defendant Hofstetter before the tribunal.
弗里德·霍夫斯特,
Friedrich Hofstetter,
本席判你有罪，终身监禁.
the tribunal finds you guilty and sentences you to life imprisonment.
法庭对被告兰谱做出判决
The marshal will produce the defendant Lampe before the tribunal.
沃纳·兰谱,
Werner Lampe,
本席判你有罪，终身监禁.
the tribunal finds you guilty and sentences you to life imprisonment.
(murmuring)
(strikes gavel)
法庭对被告欧内斯特·姜宁做出判决
The marshal will produce the defendant Ernst Janning before the tribunal.
欧内斯特·姜宁,
Ernst Janning,
本席判你有罪，终身监禁.
the tribunal finds you guilty and sentences you to life imprisonment.
他不明白
He doesn't understand.
他就是不明白
He just doesn't understand.
他知道
He understands.
(strikes gavel)
Justice lves dissenting.
我要说明我的不同意见
I wish to point out strongly my dissenting vote from the decision of this tribunal
像同海伍德和诺里斯法官所说的一样
as stated by Justice Haywood, and in which Justice Norris concurred.
被告们的所作所为,
The issue of the actions of the defendants,
自认为是效忠国家,
who believed they were acting in the best interests of their country,
这不是法庭可以审判的.
is an issue that cannot be decided in a courtroom alone.
只能客观的评价,
It can only be decided objectively,
让历史来验证.
in years to come, in the true perspective of history.
法官大人， 书放在哪里?
Where shall I put these books, Your Honour?
放在箱子里吧.
Put them in the trunk, Mr Halbestadt.
法官大人，这是给你路上吃的.
Your Honour, here's something for you to have on the plane.
你再给我吃的， 我都没地方放了.
Oh, no. If you give me any more food, I won't have any room for anything else.
但这些是甜点， 你喜欢的.
But it's strudel, the way you like it.
谢谢你的招待
Thank you. Thank you for everything.  Ja, ja.
我放到车上.  谢谢
I'll put it in the car.  Thanks.
机票、护照免检 在机场查登机证.
Tickets, passport, immunisation. I'll have your boarding pass at the airport.
三点以前机场见.
See you there no later than three o'clock.
对了，帮我问候... 她叫什么名字?
Oh, and give my regards to Miss... what was her name?
斯德尔福·爱莎.
Scheffler. Elsa.
那是你欠我的.  什么意思?
That's one you owe me.  What do you mean?
美国人今天在纽伦堡很不受欢迎.
Americans aren't very popular in Nuremberg this morning.
(dials number)
(phone rings)
(ringing continues)
下午好，法官大人  下午好
Good afternoon, Your Honour.  Good afternoon.
我受当事人欧内斯特·姜宁来此.
I came here at the request of my client, Ernst Janning.
他希望见你
He wishes to see you.
我正要去机场.
I'm just leaving for the airport.
他说对他意义重大
He says it would mean a great deal to him.
你知道法本案子的判决结果了吗?
Have you heard about the verdict in the lG Farben case?
多数人无罪， 少数人被轻判.
Most of them were acquitted. The others received light sentences.
今天判决的.  不，我不知道.
The verdict came in today.  No, I hadn't heard.
我和你打赌
I will make you a wager.
我不打赌
I don't make wagers.
绅士的赌博
A gentlemen's wager.
五年后你判处无期的罪犯将自由.
In five years, the men you sentenced to life imprisonment will be free.
罗尔福,我很欣赏你这几个月的表现
Herr Rolfe, I have admired your work in the courtroom for many months.
你特别擅长使用逻辑.
You are particularly brilliant in your use of logic.
你暗示的可能会发生.
So, what you suggest may very well happen.
逻辑上，考虑我们所处的时代.
It is logical, in view of the times in which we live.
但光依靠逻辑是不对的
But to be logical is not to be right.
上帝也不是全能的.
And nothing on God's earth could ever make it right.
有人要见你.
Someone to see you.
欧内斯特·姜宁.
Herr Janning.
海伍德法官.
Judge Haywood.
请坐.
Please, sit down.
谢谢，你要见我
Thank you. You wanted to see me.
是的，我有东西要给你
Yes. There is something I want to give you.
一份记录
A record.
我记忆中的案件记录.
A record of my cases, the ones I remember.
我想把它交给我可以信任的人,
I want to give them to someone I can trust,
在审判中我可以相信的人.
someone I felt I got to know during the trial.
谢谢
Thank you.
我会好好保管的
I'll take good care of them.
我知道审判给你带来的压力
I know the pressures that had been brought upon you.
你会被舆论批评
You will be criticised greatly.
你的决定并不明智
Your decision will not be a popular one.
但如果对你有意义的话
But, if it means anything to you,
你获得了被判罪的我的尊重.
you have the respect of at least one of the men you convicted.
在判决中， 你的判决是正义的.
By all that is right in this world, your verdict was a just one.
谢谢
Thank you.
你在法庭上要说的.
What you said in the courtroom, it needed to be said.
海伍德法官...
Judge Haywood...
我让你来的原因...
The reason I asked you to come...
那些上百万的人
Those people, those millions of people,
我从不知道会那样
I never knew it would come to that.
你一定要相信
You must believe it. You must believe it.
欧内斯特·姜宁, 你早就知道了
Herr Janning, it came to that
当你第一次判处一个无辜的人有罪时.
the first time you sentenced a man to death you knew to be innocent.